<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The names of herbes in Greke, Latin, Englishe, Duche [and] Frenche with the commune names that herbaries and apotecaries vse. Gathered by William Turner.</title>
            <author>Turner, William, d. 1568.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24359</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104970</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840700</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840700</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5227</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5227)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 155:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The names of herbes in Greke, Latin, Englishe, Duche [and] Frenche with the commune names that herbaries and apotecaries vse. Gathered by William Turner.</title>
                  <author>Turner, William, d. 1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1286] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [S. Mierdman for] John Day and Wyllyam Seres, dwellynge in Sepulchres Parish at the signe of the Resurrection a litle aboue Holbourne Conduite,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H (H8 blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks leaves H1 and H3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Botany --  Nomenclature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Botany --  Pre-Linnean works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Plant names, Popular --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5227:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5227:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of a compartment with cross-sword arms at top and a naked man and woman to the sides (not in McKerrow)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>The na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes of herbes in Greke, Latin, Engliſhe Duche &amp; Frenche wyth the commune names that Herbaries and Apoteca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries vſe. Gathered by Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5227:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5227:2"/>
            <head>To the mooſte noble &amp; mighty Prince Edward by the grace of God Duke of Summerſet Erle of Hertforde, vicount beuchamp, lord Semour vnele vnto the Kynges highneſſe of Englande, gouernour of his moſte roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all perſon and Protectour of al his realmes dominions and ſubiectes, lieuetenaunt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of al his maieſties armies boeth by lande and ſea, Treaſurer and Erlmarfhal of England, Gouernoure of the Iles of Gerneley and Ierſey, Knyght of the garter, William Turner his ſeruaunte wiſheth proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie boeth of bodie and ſoule.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N a certain litle boke whiche I ſet furth .iiii. yeres ago and ſomthynge more, which I dedicated vnto the Kynges Grace that nowe is I promiſed that if I perceyued that he woulde take in good worth that litle trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to ſet furth an herbal &amp; an other boke alſo of fiſhes. Partly to fulfyl this my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſtreight way after, I began to labour
<pb facs="tcp:5227:3"/> to make vp a latin herbal, whiche thynge I haue finiſhed .ii. yeres ago, but when I had inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded this yere to haue ſet it furth, &amp; axed the aduiſe of Phiſicianes in thys matter, their aduiſe was that I ſhoulde ceaſe from ſettynge out of this boke in latin tyll I had ſene thoſe places of Englande, wherein is moſte plentie of herbes, that I might in my herbal declare to the greate honoure of our countre what numbre of ſouereine &amp; ſtrang herbes were in Englande that were not in other nations, whoſe counſell I haue folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed deferryng to ſetout my herbal in latin, tyl that I haue ſene the weſt cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, which I neuer ſawe yet in al my lyfe, which coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of al places of England, as I heare ſay is moſte richely repleniſhed wyth al kindes of ſtraunge and wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull workes &amp; giftes of nature, as are ſtones, herbes, fiſhes and metalles when as they that moued me to the ſettyng furth of my latin herbal, hearde this ſo reaſonable an excuſe they moued me to ſet out an herbal in Engliſhe as Fuchſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us dyd in latine wyth the diſcriptions, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures and properties of as many herbes, as I had ſene and knewe, to whom I could make no other anſwere but that I had no ſuch leaſure in this vocation and place that I am nowe in, as is neceſſary for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhoulde take in hande ſuche an interpriſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5227:3"/>
            <p>But thys excuſe coulde not be admitted for both certeine ſcholars, poticaries, and alſo ſurgeans, required of me if that I woulde not ſet furth my latin herbal, before I haue ſene the weſt partes, and haue no leaſure in thys place and vocation to write ſo great a worke, at the leaſt to ſet furth my iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the names of ſo many herbes as I knew whoſe requeſt I haue acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed, and haue made a little boke, which is no morebut a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or regeſtre of ſuche bokes as I intende by the grace of God to ſet furth here after, if that I may obteine by your graces healp ſuch libertie &amp; leaſure with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t place. as ſhall be neceſſary for ſuche a purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Thys litle boke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teineth the names of the moſte parte of herbes, that all auncient au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours write of both in Greke, Lattin, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe, Duche and Frenche, I haue ſet to alſo the names whiche be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly vſed of the poticaries and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon herbaries. I haue tolde alſo the degrees of ſo many herbes as Galene the chiefe Doctour of al phiſicians hath written of, and becauſe men ſhould not thynke that I write of it that I neuer ſawe, and that Poticaries ſhoulde be excuſeleſſe when as the ryghte herbes are required of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I haue ſhewed in what places of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, Germany &amp; Italy the herbes growe
<pb facs="tcp:5227:4"/> and maye be had for laboure and money, whereof I declare and teache the names in thys preſent treates. Whiche howe profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it ſhall be vnto al the ſicke folke of thys Realme, I referre the matter vnto all them whiche are of a ryght iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in phiſicke. Thys ſmall boke of myne I dedicate vnto your grace, ſignifiyng therby, onely what mynde I beare vnto your grace, deſirynge you to take thys in good worth tyll that I maye haue leaſure and occaſion to write ſome greater &amp; more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy worke to your highneſſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> almightie God long continue in all vertue and honoure to his pleaſure Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From your graces houſe at Syon <date>Anno Dom. M.CCCCCxlviij. Martii .xv.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book_of_herbs">
            <pb facs="tcp:5227:4"/>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Abies.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bies is called in greke Elate, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh a firre tree, in duch, Ein dannen, in french Sapin, it groweth in the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes naturally and in certeyne gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted and ſet by mannes hande boeth in Englande and in Germanie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Abrotunum.</head>
               <p>Abrotonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called in greke, Abrotonon, in engliſhe Sothernwod, in duche Alfruſh, in frenche Auronne. There are two kyndes of Sothernwod, the male and the female.</p>
               <p>The male groweth plentuouſly in gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in Englande, but the female dyd I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſee growing in Englande, it is founde in Italy in plentie inough. Sothernwod is hote and dry in the thirde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Abſinthium.</head>
               <p>Abſinthium is called in greke. Apſinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in engliſhe wormwod, in Duche wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mout, in french, Abſince or Aluyne. There are three kyndes of wormwod, beſide the commune wormwod, wormwod pontike, called in latin Abunthium ponticum, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe
<pb facs="tcp:5227:5"/> maye be alſo called wormwod gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, it is called of Meſue and of the Pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries of Germany Abſinthium romanum the Coloners call it graue crut, the Freſes call it wylde roſmary. The beſte bynde of thys wormwode gentle or pontike that I haue ſene came from Rome, an other kynde of the ſame is to be had in Anwerp and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe al Germany in plentie The ſeconde kynde is called in latin Abſinthium mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num and Seryphum, it groweth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly in diches whereinto, the ſalte water vſeth at certeyne tymes to come, it is plentuous in Northumberlande by holy Ilande, and in Northfolke beſide Lin, at Barrowe in Bra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bant, and at Norden in eſt freſlande. Some take thys herbe agaynſt the trueth for pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike wormwod. The thirde kynde is called in latin Abſinthium ſantonicum, I neuer ſe the herbe but ones, it maye be called in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe frenche wormwod. Oure commune wormwod is called in latine Abſinthium ruſticum. And here is to be marked that they are farre deceiued that vſe this for po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike wormwod. I report me to Galene (xi. Methodi medendi) whether it be ſo or no. Pontike wormwod, is hote in the fyrſte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and dry in the thirde. Sea wormwod is hote in the ſeconde degree and dry in the
<pb facs="tcp:5227:5"/> fyrſte, frenche wormwod is weaker then Sea wormwod is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Acanthium.</head>
               <p>Acanthium is called in greke Acanthion, it is named of ſome herbaries carduus aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus, I haue not hearde the name of it in engliſhe, but I thynke it maye be called in engliſhe otethiſtle, becauſe the ſeedes are like vnto rough otes, or gum thiſtle, or coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thiſtle, becauſe it is gummy and the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues haue in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a thynge lyke cotten, which appeareth when they are broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It groweth in gardines in Bonony, I haue alſo ſene it in England in gardines, but neuer a brode. The herbe is of an hote &amp; a ſubtile nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Acanthus.</head>
               <p>Acanthus is called in greke Acantha, in engliſhe Branke vrlin, in duche welſhe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renklawe, in frenche branke vrſine, branca vrſina groweth in many places of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in gardines and in the greateſt plentie that I euer ſawe it, I did ſee it in my Lorde Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectours graces gardine at Syon, ſome erre ſore whiche abuſe for thys herbe berefote. The rote of bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keurſine drieth and cutteth humours lyghtly, and is of ſubtile partes, the leaues haue power metely to dryue hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours to their places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Aconitum.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:6"/>
               <p>There are .ii. kindes of the herbe called Aconitum, the one kynde is called Pardali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anches, whiche we may call in engliſhe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hardbayne or one bery. It is much in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland in a wodde beſyde Morpeth called Cottingwod. It hath foure leaues lyke vnto great pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine, &amp; in the ouermoſt top a litle blacke bery lyke a blacke morbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but blacker &amp; greater. The other kynde is called Lycoctonum, &amp; in engliſhe it maye be called wolfes bayne. But this kynde is deuided into two other kyndes, of whiche I neuer ſawe any kynde in Englande, the one hath leaues lyke crowfote, and blewe floures lyke hodes, and it is called muench kappen in duche, and it maye be called in engliſhe mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes coule or blewe wolfſbaine. The other kinde hath leaues like a playne tree or like Palma chriſt &amp; yelowe floures, thys maye be called in Engliſhe yelowe wolfesbayn. I haue ſene the former kind in great plentie vpon the alpes betwene Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uena &amp; Spelunca, and in manye gardines in Brabant, the latter kynde dyd I neuer ſe but in gardines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Acorus.</head>
               <p>Acorus groweth not in England, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are farre deceyued that vſe the ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe ſlourdeluce, whiche ſome call gladen,
<pb facs="tcp:5227:6"/> for Acorus, for Acorus is hote, bytinge and opening, but gladen is colde, vnſauery and aſtringent. I thynke that the great Galan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga is the true Acorus. If they haue not it they maye vſe Calamus aromaticus, or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarabacca for Acorus. Acorus is hote and dry in the thirde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Adiantum.</head>
               <p>Adiantum is called in greke Adianton, in duche iunkfrawen hare, of the herbaries Capillus veneris &amp; groweth not in engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for it that is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here for Adiantum is tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhomanes in Dioſcorides. Howe be it ye may vſe trichomanes for Adianto, for they are of lyke vertue. Adiantum groweth in Italy in welles, and in the alpes in watery or drepyng rockes, and eſpecially whereas the firſt water begynneth to ſtande, if that a rocke lyke a browe, hange ouer the wel or water, it may be named in engliſhe Venus heir or Colo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der maidens heir. Venus heir is in a meane tempre betwene hote &amp; colde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Agaricus.</head>
               <p>Agaricus is called in greke agaricos, in engliſh agarike, in duch danne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſthawm. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garike groweth not in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but in the alpes which deuide Germany &amp; Fraunce fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Italy. Agarike is hote &amp; dryueth awaye and breaketh in ſmal pieces, humours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:7"/>
               <head>Albucus</head>
               <p>Albucum is called alſo Haſtula regia, and in greke aſphodelos, aſphodillus gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not in Englande. It groweth in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines in Anwerp, it maye be named in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe whyte affodil, or duche daffodil, this that we take for daffodil is a kinde of Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſus mentioned in plinie, it dryueth away humours and ſendeth them abrode.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Alcea.</head>
               <p>Alcea is called in greke alcea, in Duche figmarſwortes, of the Herbaries Herba hungarica, in frenche guimane, it hath no name in engliſhe that I knowe, it maye be named Veruen mallowe, or cut mallowe. It groweth plentnouſly in Germanie at Bon by the Rhene ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Allium.</head>
               <p>Allium is called in greke ſcorodo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gliſhe garlike, in duche knobloch, in french anlouanx, it is deuided into three kyndes, the firſt kynde is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon garlike, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde kynde is called allium anguinum in latin, and ophioſcorodo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in greke, in engliſhe crowe garlike, or wylde garlike. The third kinde is called in latin Allium vrſinum, and in engliſhe Ramſey, or bucra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes or ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes. The firſt kynde groweth in gardines one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The ſeconde kynde groweth in the fiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.
<pb facs="tcp:5227:7"/> The .iij. kind groweth alſo in gardines Garlyke is hote &amp; dry in the fourth degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Alnus.</head>
               <p>Alnus is called in greke Clethra, in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe an alder tree or an aller tree, in duche erlinbaum, it groweth by water ſydes and in marriſhe middowes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Aloe.</head>
               <p>Aloe is ſo called in greke, latin &amp; engliſh, It groweth not in Englande but by the ſea ſide &amp; in Ilandes, I haue ſene it in gardines in Italy, but it dureth not in gardines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue three yeres. Aloe is after Paulus hote in the firſt degree and dry in the third. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue ſayeth that it is hote in the ſeconde and dry in the thirde, but thys is ſo to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande that it is very hote in the firſt degree and meanly hote in the ſeconde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Alſine.</head>
               <p>Alſine is called in engliſhe chike weede, in duch vogell craute, in frenche mauron, of the herbaries Morſus galline, it is moyſte and colde, it groweth on olde houſes and in al places all moſt in ſummer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Altercum.</head>
               <p>Altercum, ſiue Apollinaris is named in greke hyoſciamos, in engliſhe Henbane, in duch bylſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> craute, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Alaha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bane, of the Poticaries Iuſquiamus. It is colde in the thirde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:8"/>
               <head>Althea.</head>
               <p>Althea called alſo Hibiſcus, and Euit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, is named in greeke althaia, in Engliſhe mariſh mallowe or water mallowe, in duch ibiſh, it groweth in watery places, ſome take not as they ſhould do holyhoke for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea. Merſhe mallowe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Alyſſon Plinij.</head>
               <p>Alyſcon Plinij is a rare herbe whiche I coulde neuer ſee but once in Englande and that was a litle from Syon. It had leaues lyke madder and purple floures, it maye be named in engliſhe purple gooſgrafe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Amarantus.</head>
               <p>There are two kindes of Amara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus, the one kynde is called in greeke of Diſcorides Helichryſon, and thys kynde is founde in Italy. The other kynde is called here in Englande of ſome purple veluet floure, of other flouramore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Amygdala.</head>
               <p>Amygdala is called in greke amygdale, in engliſhe an almon tree, in duche en man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del baum, in frenche amander, it groweth in Italy and in high Germany in the fieldes, but in England, only in gardines. Almon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des haue a temparate heate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ami.</head>
               <p>Ami is called in engliſhe amy, of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaries
<pb facs="tcp:5227:8"/> ammeos, it groweth not in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, it groweth in many gardines in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in Germany. It is hote and dry in the thirde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Amomum.</head>
               <p>Amomum were Roſa hierecuntis if it ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured well, but for lacke of that, thys roſe of hierico ſemeth to be amomis.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Anagallis.</head>
               <p>Anagallis, ſiue Corchorus, is called in engliſhe pympernel, in duche gauchheyl, in french morgelina, it groweth commonly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the corne. The male hath a crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin floure, &amp; the female hath a blewe floure. They are ſomethynge hote and dry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Anagyris.</head>
               <p>Anagyris groweth not in Englande, it hath ſeede lyke a beane and I haue ſene it in Bonony, it maye be called ſtynkynge tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foly in engliſhe, or beane tree. It is hote of complexion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Anchuſa.</head>
               <p>Anchuſa groweth in ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy groundes and ſomtyme amonge the corne wyth a red roſe and leaues like Buglos, it is called in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch orchanet, it may be named in engliſhe wilde Buglos or orchanet, as the french men do. The herbe is colde and dry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Androſaemon.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:9"/>
               <p>Androſaemon is the herbe (as I door g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> whiche we call totſan, and the Poticaries falſly cal Agnus caſtus, it groweth in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines in Englande and no where elles that I haue ſene, it drieth by his natural power.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Anemone.</head>
               <p>Anemone groweth muche about Bon in Germany, I haue not ſene it in Englande, it is called of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> herbaries Herba ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, it may be called in engliſh roſe perſeley.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Anethum.</head>
               <p>Anethum is called in greeke anethon, in engliſhe and duche, dill, in french anet, anet is hote far in the ſeconde degree and is dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in driues in the ſame degree, Anethum is wronge engliſhed, of ſome, aniſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Aniſum.</head>
               <p>Aniſum is called in greke aniſon, in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe aniſe, the aniſe whiche we vſe nowe adayes is not ſo hote as Galen ſayeth that his aniſe is, for he ſayeth that aniſe is hote and dry in the thirde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Anonis.</head>
               <p>Anonis called alſo Ononis is called of the herbaries Reſta bouis, Remora aratri, and acutella, and in duche hawhekell &amp; ſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craute, and in frenche Bugraues, in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryge Shyre a whyne, it groweth in many
<pb facs="tcp:5227:9"/> places aboute cambryge. The roote of this herbe is of an hote nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Aparine.</head>
               <p>Aparine ſiue Philanthropos, ſiue Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phacocarpos is called in engliſh gooſgraſſe or Gooſehareth, in Duche Klebkraute, in frenche Grateron, the herbe ſcoureth away and dryeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Anthenus.</head>
               <p>Anthenus ſiue Chamaemelo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called in engliſhe Cammomyle, in duch camillen, in frenche camomille, Camomilla is deuided into three kyndes, the firſte kynde is called leucanthemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becauſe it hath a whyte floure and of the commune herbaries Camomilla romana, and in engliſhe cammomyle, thys herbe groweth on Rychmund grene, and in Hundſley heth in great plentie. The ſecond is called in greke chryſanthemon becauſe it hath a golden floure. I founde it once in a corne fielde betwene Baſyle and Surike, and haue neuer ſene it any where els in all my lyfe, it maye be called in engliſhe yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe camomyle. The thirde kynde is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in greeke Eranthemon becauſe it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in the ſprynge of the yere. I haue ſent it in Englande but very rare, ſome call it amariſcam rubeam, and they call it in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe red mathes, alij, red mayde wed, alij,
<pb facs="tcp:5227:10"/> purple camomyle. Camomyle is hote and drye in the fyrſte degree</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Antirrhinon.</head>
               <p>Antirrhinon is of two ſortes, the one is deſcribed of Plinie wyth leaues lyke flax, and the other is deſcribed of Dioſcorides with the leaues of pimpernel, Plinies antir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhinon groweth in many places of Germa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny in the corne fieldes, and it maye be called in engliſhe calfe ſnoute. The other kynde haue I in my gardine whoſe ſeede came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Italy, it maye be called brode calfe ſnoute.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Apios.</head>
               <p>Apios is called alſo Iſchas, chamebala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, and carica, it is called in engliſhe an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute or an earth nute, it groweth plentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlye in Northumberland, beſide morpeth &amp; in Germany betwene Redkyrke &amp; Colo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Apiaſtrum.</head>
               <p>Apiaſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiue Citrago, is named in greke Meliſſophillon, ant Meliphillo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in engliſh Baume, in duche Meleſſen oder Hertes kraut and Confili, in frenche Meleſſe. The Baume that we haue in Englande here is not the ryghte Meliſſophyllon, but it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in Germany in many gardines, and hath a greate deell better ſmell then thys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Meliſſa hath, it may be called in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe Baum gentle, Baume is hote in the
<pb facs="tcp:5227:10"/> ſeconde degree, but it dryeth not ſo muche.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Apium.</head>
               <p>Apium is named Selino<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in engliſh Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeley, in duch Peterlinge either Peterſely, in french Perſil It is hote in the ſecond degree and dry in the middeſt of the thyrde. Some vſe for it wyth an errour Paludapio, that is Smallage for apio. Perſeley groweth no where that I knowe, but only in gardines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ariſtolochia.</head>
               <p>Ariſtolochia is of three ſortes. The fyrſt is called in latin ariſtolochia rotunda, and it may be named in engliſhe round Ofter Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior aſtrolochia, or round hertworte. Some abuſe for thys herbe, Holwort, whiche is in Pleni Capnos phragmites. But their error is eaſely perceyued by the readynge of the diſcription of Dioſcorides. This kind gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not in Englande, but in Italy and in Fraunce plentuouſly. The ſecond is called Ariſtolochia longa, and it groweth very li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in Englande that I haue ſene, but about Bon in Germany it groweth in many hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by the vineyardes, but there it bringeth furth no fruite, but beſyde Lake decome, it bryngeth furth fruite lyke blacke peares and ſeede lyke mennes hertes, thys kynde may be called in engliſhe longe Hertworth or longe Aſtolochia The third kinde is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:5227:11"/> Clematites &amp; it may be called in engliſh ſmall Hertworte, it groweth in high Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, in Baſile. Herteworte is hote and drye about the thirde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Armoracia.</head>
               <p>Armoratia is named in greke Raphanis it groweth not in England that I wotte of, but it groweth in Italy and it is called Lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moratia, it myght be called in engliſhe if we had it, wyld Radiſh, it is hote of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Arum.</head>
               <p>Arum is called in greke aron, in engliſh Cuckopintell, Wake Robin, or Rampe, in duche Pſaffen bynde, in frenche Vidchaen, the Poticarie calleth it Pes vituli, Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria minor, Luph minus groweth in euery hedge almoſt in Englande aboute townes in the ſpryng of the yere. Some wryte that it is but hote &amp; drie in the fyrſt degree, howe be it our aron is hote in the thirde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Arbutus.</head>
               <p>Arbutus groweth in Italy, it hath leaues like Quicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree, a fruite lyke a ſtrawbery, wherfore it may be called in engliſh ſtraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery tree, or an arbute tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Arthemiſia.</head>
               <p>Arthemiſia otherwyſe called Parthenis, is commonly called in engliſhe mugworte, and in duch Bifuſſe, it is not the very ſame
<pb facs="tcp:5227:11"/> that Dioſcorides deſcribeth. I ſaw the right Mugwort in an Ilande beſide Venice, and it may be called in engliſhe litle Mugwort. Arthemiſia is of three ſortes, the fyrſt is the herbe that I cal ſea Mugworte, the ſeconde kynde after Fuchſius, is Feuerfew, and the thyrde kynde Tanſey. Thys brode and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon kynde maye be vſed for the ryght tyll we maye get better. Mugworte heateth in the ſeconde degree, and dryeth either vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently in the ende of the fyrſt degree, or els lyghtly in the begynnyng of the ſeconde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Arundo.</head>
               <p>Arundo is called in greeke Calamos, in engliſhe a reed, in duch Ein ror oder ried, in frenche nug roſeau, it groweth in water ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, &amp; in fennes, &amp; ſuch other watery places</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Aſarum.</head>
               <p>Aſarum is named in greke aſaron, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe azarabacca or Folefote, in duche Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelwortz, in frenche Cabaret, it is hote and dry in the third degree. It groweth in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many wylde vnder Haſell trees, wherupon it hath the name. It groweth in Englande onely in gardines that I wotte of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Aſcyron.</head>
               <p>Aſcyron is not very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon in England, howe be it I ſawe it thys laſt yere in Syon parck, it hath a fourſquared ſtalke, &amp; is like
<pb facs="tcp:5227:12"/> ſaynte Iohans graſſe, but it is greater and not wyth ſuche holes as are in ſaynte Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hans graſſe, wherefore it maye be called in engliſh ſquare ſaint Iohans graſſe or great ſaynt Iohans graſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Aſclepias.</head>
               <p>Aſclepias is called of the Herbaries Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundinaria, of the duche men Schwalben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wirt, and of ſome poticaries Vincetoxicum. It groweth in Germany in highe moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, and in ſtony grounde amonge bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſhes I haue not ſene it in England, it may be called in engliſhe, Swallowurt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Aſparagus.</head>
               <p>Aſparagus is of .ij. kyndes, the one kinde is called in latin aſparagus altilis, or aſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragus alone, of the Poticaries ſparagus, in Engliſhe Sperage, in Duche Spargen, in french Eſperage, it groweth very plentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in the Ilandes of caſt Freeſeland, but in Englande it groweth no where els that I knowe, but in gardines. The other is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in latin Corruda or aſparagus ſylue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris I neuer ſawe thys kynde but onely in Italy in the mounte aperune, it maye be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in engliſhe pricky Sperage, becauſe it is all full of pryckes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Aſplenum.</head>
               <p>Aſplenum or aſplenium named in greke
<pb facs="tcp:5227:12"/> aſplenon, or Scolope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drion, in duche Stein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferne, is called of the poticaries Citterache. It maye be called in engliſhe Citterach, or Scaleferne, or Fingerferne. Thys herbe groweth communely in greate rockes and in moyſte walles, it is very muche in big he Germany beſyde Embis hath, and beſyde S. Goweris. I heare ſay that it is alſo ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous in the weſt countrey here in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Aſtragalus.</head>
               <p>Aſtragalus is called in lowe duche lande Erde nut, &amp; in Berglande Erdeklin, it may be called in engliſh peaſerthnut. It groweth in the mountaynes of Germany, and hath leaues and ſtalkes lyke a peaſe, blacke litle rotes with knoppes lyke acornes, Fuchſius toke thys herbe to be apios, but the diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion agreeth not. Aſtragalus hath a nature to drye, I haue ſene thys herbe of late in Coome parke more aſtringe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Atractilis altera.</head>
               <p>Atractilis altera, named of the potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Cardo benedictus, and ſo is it alſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in Engliſhe, it groweth no where in Englande that I knowe, but in gardines.</p>
               <p>It dryeth humours by nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Atriplex.</head>
               <p>Atriplex called in greke atraphaxys, or
<pb facs="tcp:5227:13"/> Chryſolachano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in engliſh Orech or Orege, in Duche Milten, in Frenche arroches, is moyſte in the ſeconde degree and colde in the fyrſte, it groweth in gardines &amp; in ſome Cornefieldes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Auena.</head>
               <p>Auena named in greeke Bromos, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe Otes or hauer, in duche Haber or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, in french auoine, is ſomthing of a colde nature and a ſtoppyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Bacchar.</head>
               <p>Bacchar or Baccaris is the herbe (as I thynke) that we cal in engliſh Sage of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, but I wyll determine nothynge in thys mattertyl I haue ſene further. Let ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men examine and iudge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Balanus myrepſica.</head>
               <p>Balanus myrepſica, is called of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaries Ben, and ſo mayt it be alſo named in engliſhe, it ſcoureth and cutteth wyth a certeyne aſtriction. It groweth not in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropa that I haue hearde tel of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ballote.</head>
               <p>Ballote named of ſome marrubiaſtrum or marrubium nigrum is named in engliſh ſtynkyng Horehound or blacke Horehound in duche ſtynkend andorne, in frenche mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubin nore, it groweth in hedges commune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in euery countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:13"/>
               <head>Barba Hirci.</head>
               <p>Barba Hirci named in greeke Trago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pogon or Come, groweth in the fieldes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute London plentuouſly, and it groweth muche in the middowes of Colon and in many places in duch land. The duch herbe hath ſome bitternes in the roote &amp; a whyte ſeede, but oures is ſwete and hath blacke ſeede, therfore oures is the better herbe. It maye be called in engliſhe gotes bearde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Bellis.</head>
               <p>Bellis or Bellius named in Engliſhe a Daſie, is called of the Herbaries Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolida minor, in duch Maſſible and Cleyn Iritlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſen, in french Margarites or Petit conſyre. Daſies growe in al grene places in greate plentie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Beta.</head>
               <p>Beta named in greeke Seutlon &amp; Teut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, is called in Engliſhe a Bete, in Duche Mangolt, in frenche Porree, on Iotte. It is called of Plenie and Theophraſtus, Sicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la. Betes growe in England, as farre as I knowe in gardines only.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Betonica</head>
               <p>Betonica called in Greeke Ceſtron or Pſychotrophio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is named in engliſhe Beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or Beton, in duche Betonien, in frenche Betoine, it groweth muche in woddes and
<pb facs="tcp:5227:14"/> wylde foreſtes. Betony is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Betonica Pauli aeginete.</head>
               <p>Betonica Pauli, is a litle herbe growing not higher then Peny ryal wyth leaues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo lyke Peny ryal wyth ſeedes in coddes lyke Burſa paſtoris, it groweth ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuouſly in Germany about Bon, and in Englande in a parke beſyde London, it maye be called in engliſhe Paules Betony or wodde Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ryal.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Betula.</head>
               <p>Betula or as ſome wryte it, betulla, is called in greeke Semida, in engliſhe a birch tree or a birke tree, in duche ein birck baum, in frenche bouleau ou beula. It groweth in woddes and foreſtes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Blitum.</head>
               <p>Blitum is named in greeke blito<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or bleto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in duch maier, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch dublite, I neuer ſaw it in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d but in my lordes gardine, and there it was vnknowen. It may be named a blete. Blete after Galene is colde &amp; moyſte in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Botrys.</head>
               <p>Botrys is called in engliſh Oke of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, in duche trauben krante, in frenche pijmen as ſome teache. It groweth in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines muche in Englande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Braſſica.</head>
               <p>Braſſica is named in greeke krambe, in
<pb facs="tcp:5227:14"/> engliſhe colewuries, cole or keele, in duche kol, in frenche chauls, in the Poticaries latin caulis.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Braſſica marina.</head>
               <p>Braſſica marma is called in greke krambe thalaſtia, in duche meer kole, in frenche ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dana. I haue not ſeene it in England, but I thynke that it groweth ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuouſly in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande It may be called in engliſh ſeafolfote it groweth plentuouſly in eaſt Freeſlande aboute the bankes of diches whereinto the ſalt water cometh at euery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ynge tyde, it groweth alſo much in middowes by the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde, whiche are ſomtyme ouerflowed with the ſalte water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Braſſica ſylueſtris.</head>
               <p>Braſſica ſylueſtris groweth in Douer cliffes where as I haue onely ſeene it in al my life. It may be named in engliſh ſea cole</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Bryon thalaſſion.</head>
               <p>Bryon thalaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> named in latin Muſcus marinus is of two ſortes, the one is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of Dioſcorides to be very ſmall after the maner of heires, thys kynde is of two ſortes. The one kynde is called Vſnea ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rina, &amp; it may be called in engliſh ſea moſſe, it groweth aboute ſtones and ſhelles in the ſea. An other of the ſame kynde is called of certeyne Herbaries Corallina. Both theſe
<pb facs="tcp:5227:15"/> haue very ſmal brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches, the firſt like wod, the other lyke ſtone. The other kynde is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed of Plenie &amp; Theophraſtus to haue leaues lyke letties, and thys kynde is called in engliſhe ſlauke. It groweth in the ſea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſhelles and ſtones alſo. It coleth and byndeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Bryonia.</head>
               <p>Bryonia called in greeke Ampelos leuce in engliſh bryonie or wylde Neppe, in duch wylde Kur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> teufels Kirs, it is named in frenche C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nree and de fen ardant. It groweth in many places of Englande in hedges. It ſcoureth awaye and dryeth vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Bugloſſum.</head>
               <p>Bugloſſum called of the Poticaries bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rago, is called in engliſhe borage, in duche borretſch, in french borache, borage is moyſt and warme. I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are ſaye that there is a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter kynde of Bugloſſe founde of late in Spayne, but I haue not ſeene that kynde as yet. The commune bugloſſe that we vſe, is not cirſion, as afterwardes I ſhal declare but a certeyne kynde of ryght bugloſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Bulbine.</head>
               <p>Bulbine called in Duche hundes vllich maye be called in engliſhe dogges Leike, it groweth much about Bon in Germany. It hath a rounde roote and a yealowe flower.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:15"/>
               <head>Bunium.</head>
               <p>Bunium is a rare herbe in Englande, to me at the leaſt, for I coulde neuer fynde it here, but Lucas the reader of Dioſcorides in Bonomy ſhewed it me. It maye be called in engliſhe ſquare perſeley. Bunium is hote of complexion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Buthalmus.</head>
               <p>Buthalmus is lyke Chryſanthemon, but the floure is a greate deele greater. I haue ſeene it in Italy and in high Germany, but no where in Englande. It may be called in engliſhe Oxeye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Buxus.</head>
               <p>Buxus named in greeke Pyxos is called in engliſhe box, in duch buckſz baume, and in frenche bouys.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Calamintha.</head>
               <p>Calamintha is of three kyndes, the firſte kynde is lyke wilde Meriorum and it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth muche about Syon in Englande, and by Bon in Germany. It maye be called in engliſhe buſh calamint, becauſe it groweth euer amonge the buſſhes, or hore calamynt. The ſeconde kynde groweth muche in the corne, and therfore it is called in duch corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynt. It is alſo called in engliſh corne mint and calamynt. The thyrde kynde is called in latin Nepeta, in engliſhe Nepe, in Duche
<pb facs="tcp:5227:16"/> Katzenkrante oder Katzenmuntz, in frenche herbe Anchat. Calamynt is hote and dry in the third degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Caltha.</head>
               <p>Caltha is called of the Herbaries calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula, in engliſhe a Marygolde, in Duche Ringebloumen, in frenche Soulſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Canabis.</head>
               <p>Canabis is called in Engliſhe Hemp, in duche Hanffe in french chanure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cantabrica.</head>
               <p>Cantabrica of Plenie, is called in engliſh wylde Gelouer or geleſloure, in duch wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der neglebloum, in frenche Armoris. Some cal the ſame herbe Garyophilſata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſilueſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Capnos.</head>
               <p>Capnos called in latin Fumaria, and in engliſhe Fumitarie, in duche Kernell oder Erdrauch, in frenche furniterre, it groweth amonge the corne, and it hath a ſharp and a bytter qualitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Capnos phragmites.</head>
               <p>Capnos prior Pliuij, or Capnos phrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites in Theophraſtus, is called in duche, Holewurte, and falſly of the commune ſorte Ariſtolochia rotunda. It groweth plentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in Germany aboute Bon in the hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, it may be called in engliſhe Holewurte</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Capparis.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:16"/>
               <p>Capparis or Inturis is called in engliſh Capers, in duche Kappers, in frenche Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres. Capers is hote in the ſeconde degree, and dry in the thirde after Auerois.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Carduus.</head>
               <p>Carduus called in latin Scolimus after Galene, Aetius &amp; Paulus is a ſundry herbe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cinara. But other authours make only thys difference that Carduus ſhoulde be wylde Archichoke and Cinara ſhoulde be the gardin Archichoke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Careum.</head>
               <p>Careum called alſo Carium, and in greeke Karos, is called in engliſhe Carruwayes, in high duch Weiſz kymmer, in lowe duch Hoffe cumyn, in frenche Carni, the potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries cal it alſo Carni, it is almoſte hote and dry in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Carex.</head>
               <p>Carex is called in engliſhe a Sege, it gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth in fennes and in watery places, it is called in Northumberla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Shearegraſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cutteth mennes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des that touche it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Caſſutha.</head>
               <p>Caſſutha called in greke Caſſitas, is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in engliſh Doder, in duch Filtz kraut, Doder, and wrang, in french Goute de line, the Poticaries cal it Cuſcutam and Poda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram lini. Some abuſe thys herbe when it
<pb facs="tcp:5227:17"/> groweth aboute ſmal graſſe, or Tyme, or Sauery for Epithymo of the olde writers. Howe be it they are deceyued. For the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that groweth about Tyme is only E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithymum Meſues, and not Galeni and Dioſcoridis. Doder groweth aboute Flax, Tares, Nettels, Tyme, Sauery, Hoppes, and many other ſuche lyke, it is much more ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuous in Germany the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Caſtanea.</head>
               <p>Caſtanea called Caſtonos in greke, and of ſome Dus balanos, is named in engliſhe a Cheſnut tree in duche en Keſten baum, in frenche Caſtaiginey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Celtis.</head>
               <p>Celtis named in greke Lotos is called in frenche as Geſnere ſayeth, Algſier or Ledo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mier, but how that it is called in engliſh and in duche I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not tel, for I neuer ſawe it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Germany nor in Englande, but I haue ſeene it in Italy, it hath a leafe lyke a Nettel, therfore it may be called in engliſhe Ntetel tree or Lote tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Centaurium.</head>
               <p>Centaurium is of two ſortes, the one is called centaurium magnum and it is called of the Poticaries Ruponticum, and in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe Rupontike. It groweth onely in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, I neuer ſawe it ſauyng only in Italy
<pb facs="tcp:5227:17"/> and Germany. The ſeconde kynde is called in latin Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aurium minus, in engliſhe Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, in duch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſent gulden, in french Fiel be terre. Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>torie ſcouteth away &amp; dryeth vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Centunculus.</head>
               <p>Centunculus named in greke Guapha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion is named in duche Rurkraut and in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe in ſome places Cartaphilago. Howe be it that is an other herbe as afterwardes I ſhal declare. It maye be called in engliſhe Chafweede, it is called in Yorke ſupre cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weede.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cepe.</head>
               <p>Cepe or Cepa called in greeke Crommy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is of diuerſe ſortes, the firſt kynde is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in latin Cepa aſcaloma, in greke Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myon aſkalonton, and in engliſh a Scalion. The ſeconde is called Crom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>yon Schiſton, in engliſhe in ſome place Hole leke, it were better to call it Wynterouyon, becauſe it hath blades as Onions and not like ſeekes and endureth all the wynter. The Duche cal thys Onyon Seer or Suer. I ſee it no where elles but in gardines. Onyons are hote in the fourth degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cepaea.</head>
               <p>Cepaea is diuerſly deſcribed of Dioſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides &amp; Plan, Cepaea that Dioſcorides de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth
<pb facs="tcp:5227:18"/> as I iudge is the herbe whiche is called in engliſhe Brooklem, and in Duche Bauchhung. It groweth in water ſydes, and by brookes, &amp; ſprynges. Cepaea Plinij groweth by the ſea ſyde, and becauſe it is very lyke Purcellayne, it maye be called in engliſhe ſea Purcellayne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Chamaecypariſſus.</head>
               <p>Chamaecypariſſus is ſuppoſed of ſome men to be the herbe that we cal Lauander cotton, whoſe opinion as I do not vtterly reiect, yet I founde an herbe in the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes aboue Bon, which being in al poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes much more lyke a Cypres tree, then La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uander cotten is, me thynke is rather Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maecypariſſus then it is, it may be called in engliſhe heath Cypres, becauſe it groweth amonge heath, or dwarfe Cypres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Camedrys.</head>
               <p>Chamedrys called in latin Triſſago, in engliſhe Germander or engliſhe Triacle, in duche Bamanderlin, in frenche Geliman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. It is called of the Potecaries Chame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dryos. Germander groweth in the rockes of Germany ouer agaynſte Byng beſyde Cre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fiel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. In England I ſawe it no where ſauyng onely in gardines. It is hote &amp; drye in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Chameleuce.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:18"/>
               <p>Chamelence named in latine Populago, Farfagium and Farranu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberlande a Lucken gollande. It gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in watery middowes with a leafe like a water Roſe, wherfore it may be called al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Petie nunefar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Chamepence.</head>
               <p>Chamepence is a very rare herbe, whiche I neuer ſawe growyng, ſauyng only in the aſpes, it boweth lyke the eare of rye, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may be called in engliſhe Aſpeare or Petie Larix.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Chamepitys.</head>
               <p>Chamepitys called in latin Aiuga, and of the Poticaries Iua muſcata, is called in duche Ye leuger, and in french Ine muſcate and it maye be called in engliſhe Grounde pyne. It groweth muche in the mount Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penine beſyde Bonony and aboue Bon in Germany. I haue not ſeene it in Englande. It is drye in the thyrde degree and hote in the ſeconde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Chondrilla.</head>
               <p>Chondrilla is not in Englande that I haue ſeene, it is muche in highe Germany and becauſe it hath leaues lyke Succorye, and ſtalkes lyke Ryſſhes, it maye be named in engliſhe Ryſhe Succory or gum Succo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry becauſe it hath a clammy humour in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:19"/>
               <head>Cicerbita.</head>
               <p>Cicerbita is named in greeke Sogthas, in engliſhe a Sow thiſtle, in duche Salen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koel or genſz diſtel, in frenche Lattero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune inough in al countreis. The nature of the herbe is to coole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cicer.</head>
               <p>Cicer is called in greeke Erebinthos, in duche Kicherus, kicherbs and Ziſſerne, in frenche Cich ou Pois ciches Cicer is much in Italy and in Germany. I haue ſene them but ſeldom in Englande. Cicer may be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in engliſh Cich, or ciche peaſe, after the frenche tonge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cicercula.</head>
               <p>Cicercula named in greeke Lathyros, gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth in Germany in greate plentie aboue Bon, the puls maye be called in Engliſhe cichlynge, or litle or Petie ciche.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cicera.</head>
               <p>Cicera &amp; cicercula diffre by theſe markes. Cicercula hath white ſeede and ful of ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and Cicera hath blacke ſeedes. Cicera maye be called in engliſhe blacke cichlynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cicuta.</head>
               <p>Cicuta is called in greeke Concion, in engliſhe Homlocke or Hemlocke, in duche Sheirlynge, in frenche Cigue or ſecu. The leaues of oure H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mlocke are not ſo ſmal, as
<pb facs="tcp:5227:19"/> Dioſcorides requireth in his cicuta. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>locke is told in the extremitie, that is in the fourth degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cingulum.</head>
               <p>Cingulum is named in greeke Zoſter, it groweth in the ſea, &amp; is like a gyrdel, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it maye be named in engliſhe, fyſſhers gyrdle or ſea gyrdel, or ſea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elte. I haue ſene it in eaſt Freſlande by the ſea ſyde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cirſium.</head>
               <p>Cirſium named in greeke Cirſion hath ben ſuppoſed of many to be oure Bogl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, but they are deceyued. I thynke that oure Lang debefe ſhoulde be the ryghte Cirſim, if it had purple floures, as it hath yealowe. Howbeit I thynke that it is the right Cuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the coloure of the herde is diuerſe in diuerſe places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ciſthus.</head>
               <p>Ciſthus groweth plentuouſly in Italy, and one kinde of ciſthus groweth in my Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des gardine in Syon. Ciſthus is called of ſome Herbaries Roſa canina and roſago. It that groweth in Italy, whiche I ſawe in Ferraria hath ſhorter leaues, then thys ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthus that groweth in Syon. Ciſthus may be named in engliſh ciſtſage or buſhſage, for the lykenes that it hath with ſage. Ciſthus bindeth and dryeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:20"/>
               <head>Ciſtus ladanifera.</head>
               <p>Ciſthus ladanifera hath lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger and ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler leaues, then hath the other ciſthus, it gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth muche in Spayne and alſo in Italy, whereas I haue ſene it, it maye be named in England, London or Ladonſhrub. It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt hote in the ſeconde degree and bindeth ſomthynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Clematis daphnoides.</head>
               <p>Clematis daphnoides is called of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin wryters Vinca peruinca, and in engliſhe Perewincle, in duche ingrien, and in frenche peruitica.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Clematis altera.</head>
               <p>Clematis altera is not wythwynde, as Ruellius geſſed, but an other herbe far vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke, which I ſawe once in Farraria, it hath ſharper &amp; lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger leaues the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peruinca hath. It may be named in engliſhe buſh Perewincle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Clinopodium.</head>
               <p>Clinopodium groweth plentuouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute Bon by the Rehne ſyde. I heare ſaye that it groweth alſo about Oxford. It may be called in engliſhe horſe Tyme, becauſe it is like great Tyme, it is hote and dry in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Clymenum.</head>
               <p>Clymenum ſemeth not to be al one herbe in Plime &amp; Dioſcorides, clymenum of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſcorides,
<pb facs="tcp:5227:20"/> is water Betonie as I ſuppoſe called of ſome Herbaries Scrofularia ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior. Clymenos of Plinie ſemeth to ibe an herbe called in duche aboute Colon, ſaynte Iohns kraute, it groweth in wodes aboute hedges, and the other kynde groweth euer in water ſydes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cnecus.</head>
               <p>Cnecus or cuicus is called in greeke cue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, in engliſhe Baſtarde ſaffron or mocke ſaffron, in duche wylde ſaffron, in frenche ſaffran baſtarde, it is hote in the thyrde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. It is muche in highe Germany ſowen in fieldes, as ſaffron is ſet here. The Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries call thys herbe carthamus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cholchicum.</head>
               <p>Cholchicum is abuſed of ſome Potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for Hermodactylus. Cholchicum hath leaues and ſeedes in ſommer, and flowres lyke ſaffron flowres aboute Mihelmeſſe. It is muche in Germany about Bon in moyſt middowes and in woddes. It maye be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in engliſhe, wylde ſaffron.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Colocaſia.</head>
               <p>Colocaſia called in greeke Cyamos ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptios and in latin Faba, alſo Egyptia, it may be called in engliſh a Bene of Egypt. I haue ſene the right colocaſia in Italy, and a kynde of the ſame in Germany.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:21"/>
               <head>Colutea.</head>
               <p>Colutea as Ruellius iudgeth is the tree, which is called of the Poticaries Sene, and in engliſhe Sene, I haue ſene it a litle from Bououy in the mount Appennine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Coniza.</head>
               <p>Coniza is of two ſortes, the greater and the leſſe. I haue ſene both the kyndes in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betwene Cremona and Farraria by the Padus banke, the leſſe groweth muche in Germany by the Rhene, they are both hote and dry in the thyrde degree. Coniza maye be called in engliſhe Flebayne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Conſiligo.</head>
               <p>Conſiligo whereof is made mention in Cohimella and Pleme, is the herbe whiche is called in engliſh hearfot, in duch Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wurtz, in frenche Pate d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lyon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Conuoluulus.</head>
               <p>Conuoluulus called in greeke Helxine Ciſſampelos, it is the herbe which is called of the herbaries Volubilis, in engliſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynde or byndeweede, in duche Winden, in french Lizet, lizeron, or campanet. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulus wyndeth it ſelfe aboute herbes and buſſhes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Coriandrum.</head>
               <p>Coria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Corianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called in greeke Corio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; coriano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in engliſhe Cola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der or cori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,
<pb facs="tcp:5227:21"/> in duch koria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, &amp; in french coria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre. It is hote in the fyrſt degree after Auerrho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, I thynke that he meaneth of the ſeede</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cornus.</head>
               <p>Cornus is called in greke crania, in duch thierlinbaume, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Coruner or coriner, the male of thys kynde haue I ſene ofte in Germany, but neuer yet in Englande. It maye be called in engliſhe longe chery tree. The female is ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuous in Englande &amp; the buchers make prickes of it, ſome cal it Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driſe or dog <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ree, howe be it there is an other tree that they cal dogriſe alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Corunopus.</head>
               <p>Coronopus named in greke coronopous is called in Cambryge, herbe Iue, and it myghte alſo wel be named crowfore wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breade, it groweth muche aboute Shene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue London, it loueth wel to growe by the ſea bankes alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Corylus.</head>
               <p>Corylus called in greeke Carya Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tike, is called in engliſhe an Haſyle tree, in duche Ein haſeſſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, in french couldre. The fruite of thys is called in latin, Auellana.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Crataeogonum.</head>
               <p>Cataeogonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiue crataegonum, is the herbe which the herbaries name Parſicari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, engliſhe men cal Arſſinerte, duche men
<pb facs="tcp:5227:22"/> floechkraut, and frenche men Raſſel and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, it groweth in watery &amp; moyſt places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Crithmus.</head>
               <p>Crithmus named alſo crithamus &amp; Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis is called in engliſhe Sampere, it is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of ſome Herbaries creta marina, it gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth much in rockes &amp; cliffes beſide Douer</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Crocus.</head>
               <p>Crocus is named in greeke Crokos, in engliſhe Saffron or ſafforne, in duche, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffran, in frenche Safrone, it is hote in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde degree and dry in the fyrſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cucumis.</head>
               <p>Cucumis is called in greeke Sicyos or Sicys, in engliſh a cucummer, in duch Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumren, in french a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>combre. It is in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner colde and moyſt in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cucumis ſylueſtris.</head>
               <p>Cucumis ſylueſtris called in greeke Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cys agrios, &amp; of other cucumis anguinus, of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Herbaries Aſininus, groweth ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly aboute Bonony in Italy, &amp; in ſome gardines in Englande. It maye be called in engliſhe wylde cucummer or leapyng cucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. It is hote in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cucurbita.</head>
               <p>Cucurbita is called in greeke Colocyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, in engliſhe a Gourde, in duche Kurbſz, intrenche Courge, a Gourde is colde and
<pb facs="tcp:5227:22"/> moyſte in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cucurbita ſylueſtris.</head>
               <p>Cucurbita ſylueſtris is called in greeke Colocynthis, it is called in engliſhe, and of the apoticaries coloquintida. It groweth in certeyne gardines in Germany.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cuminum.</head>
               <p>Cuminum is called in greeke Cyminon in engliſhe cummyn, in duche cummich or cumyn, in frenche cumyne. Cumine is hote in the thyrd degree, it groweth in Candy, I haue not ſene it in Englande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cupreſſus.</head>
               <p>Cupreſſus is named in greeke Cypa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſos, in engliſhe a cypreſſe tree. Cypreſſes growe in great plentie in my Lordes graces gardine at Syon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cyanus.</head>
               <p>Cyanus is named in greeke Cyanos, in engliſh Blewbottel or a blewblaw, in duch Blaw Cornblowme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in french Blaueole, or blanet, the herbe groweth among the corne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cyclaminus.</head>
               <p>Cyclaminus otherwyſe called Ichthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oteron, Rapum terre, vmbilicus terre, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis porcinus, is named in duche erd apſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeubrot, in french payne de porceu, it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth plentuouſly beſyde Bonony in the mount Appenine, and in ſwechyrlande be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde
<pb facs="tcp:5227:23"/> Wallenſe, I heare ſaye that it groweth alſo in the welt countrey of Englande, but I haue not hearde yet the engliſhe name of it. Me thynke that it might wel be called in engliſhe Rape Violet becauſe it hath a roote lyke a Rape &amp; floores lyke a Violet or ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brede. It is hote and dry in the begynnynge of the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cynagloſſus.</head>
               <p>Cynagloſſus the ſecond of Plenie, which he deſcribeth to haue litle bures, is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cynagloſſus, whiche the Paticaries vſe, and is called in engliſhe Houndes tong or dogs tonge. It groweth in ſandy groundes and about cities &amp; townes, I haue not ſene that I wotte of yet cynagloſſum Tioſeoridis, whiche hath no ſtalke at al.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cynorrhodus.</head>
               <p>Cynorrhodus named of the latines Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa canina, is called in engliſhe a ſwete brere or an Eglentyne, in duche wylde Roſen or Eglenter, in trenche Roſe ſauage or eglen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier. It groweth in Germany muche in the fieldes and in gardines in Englande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cyperus.</head>
               <p>Cyperus is called in latin Iuncus angu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſus, in engliſh, engliſhe Gala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gal, in duch wyld Galge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Souchet. The beſt &amp; righteſt Cyperus groweth in Rome in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne
<pb facs="tcp:5227:23"/> gardines. One kynde of it which we call Galangal groweth in many gardines in Englande. Cyperus Babilonions is the commune Balanga ſolde in the Puticaries ſhoppes, after Ruellus and after the ſame, cyperus indicus is a roote called of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaries curcuma. Cyperus is hote &amp; dry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cytiſus.</head>
               <p>Cytiſus groweth plentuouſly in mount Appennine, I haue had it alſo growyng in my gardine in high Germany, I haue not ſene it in Englande. Cytiſus may be called in engliſhe tretrifoly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Daphnoides</head>
               <p>Daphnoides called of the commune ſort Laureola, in engliſhe, Lauriel, Lorel or Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, groweth ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuouſly in hedges in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and ſome abuſe the ſeede of it for coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognidio.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Daueus.</head>
               <p>There are many kyndes of Daueus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Dioſcorides, three at the leaſt, wherof I knowe none ſuerly but one, whiche is called in latin paſtinaca ſylueſtris, in engliſh wild carot, &amp; in greeke Staphilitios agrios, for the other kindes ye may vſe carawey ſeede, or carot ſeede. Some learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe hold that both the Saxifrages, that is the engliſhe, and the Italion may be
<pb facs="tcp:5227:24"/> occupied for Daueo. Daucus is ſharpe and heateth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Dictamnus.</head>
               <p>Dictamnus groweth in Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy and hath rounde thicke rough leaues, I haue not ſene It growyng, but dry ofte. It may be had in Venice &amp; at Anwerp. Some abuſe for thys Fracinella, Dictamnus maye be named in engliſhe righte Dittany, for ſome cal Lepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium alſo Dittany.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Dipſacos.</head>
               <p>Dipſacos called in latin Labrum Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, is called in engliſh wilde Taſel, in duch Karten diſtel, in french Chardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Carder. it groweth by dich ſides &amp; in watery groun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, it is dry in the ſecond degree. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Herbaries cal this herbe Virgam paſtoris.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Dracunculus.</head>
               <p>Dracunculus is named in greeke Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contia, in engliſhe Dragon, in duche groſſe naterwurtz, in french Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarie. The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaries cal it Serpentaria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maiorem. It gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth onely in gardines in Englande, it is ſharper then Aron.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Dryopteris.</head>
               <p>Dryopteris groweth in olde Okes and in olde walles with wal Saxifrage &amp; Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chomanes in Loua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Auwerp. Some ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe it for ryght Venus heir. I haue founde
<pb facs="tcp:5227:24"/> it in buſhe rootes ofte tymes in Germany, it may be called in engliſhe petie Ferne, or okeferne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ebulus.</head>
               <p>Ebulus is called in greeke Chameacte, in engliſh Walwurt or Danewurt, in duch Allich, in frenche Hieble, it groweth abrode in Cambryge fieldes in great plentie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Elatine.</head>
               <p>Elatine is lyke wythwynde, but it hath ſeedes and floures lyke Buckwheate, it gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth amonge the corne &amp; in hedges, it maye be named in engliſhe running Buckwheate or bynde corne, it is colde in the roote.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Elioſelinum.</head>
               <p>Elioſelinum is called in latin Paluda pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um of Gaza, it is called in engliſhe Smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, it groweth in watery places and alſo in gardines. Some haue taken thys for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio, but the errour was not very greate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are lyke in ſtrength.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ephemerum non lethale.</head>
               <p>Ephemeru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called in duch meyblumle, in french Muguet. It groweth plentuouſly in Germany, but not in England that euer I coulde ſee, ſauynge in my Lordes gardine at Syon. The Poticaries in Germany do name it Litium co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nallium, it maye be called in engliſhe May Lilies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:25"/>
               <head>Erice.</head>
               <p>Erice is called in greeke Ereice, it is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in engliſh Heth hather, or ling, in duch Heyd, in french Bruyer, it groweth on fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th and wyld mores, ſome uſe to make bruſſhes of heath both in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and in Germany.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Eruca</head>
               <p>Eruca is named in greeke Euzomos, in engliſhe rokket, in duch alſo rokket, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Roquetie. After Dioſcorides &amp; Plinie there are two kyndes of rokket. The one is gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine Rokket, whiche is muche greater then the other, &amp; it hath a white leafe, ſome abuſe thys for whyte muſtarde. The other kynde called in latin Eruca ſylueſtris, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called in engliſhe Rokket, it hath a yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe floure, &amp; both theſe kyndes are founde no where in Englande, ſauynge onely in gardines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Eruilia.</head>
               <p>Eruilia groweth in Italy, I haue had it alſo growynge in my gardine in Colon. If is lyke a peaſe, the ſhale is roughe wythin, and the ſeede hath litle blacke ſpottes in it, It maye be called in engliſhe peale eruyle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Eruum.</head>
               <p>Eruum is named in greeke Orobos, it groweth in Italy and in highe Germany aboute Menſe, it is greater &amp; bytterer then
<pb facs="tcp:5227:25"/> a Fych, it maye be called in engliſhe bitter Fyche. Bitter Fyche dryeth farre in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde degree, and is hote in the fyrſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Eryngium.</head>
               <p>Eryngium is named in engliſhe ſea Hul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or ſea H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly, it groweth plentuouſly in Englande by the ſea ſyde. The herbes that Fuchſius and Riffius paint for Eryngium are not the true Eryngium.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Euonymus.</head>
               <p>Euonymus is called of ſome wryters Fuſago or Fuſaria, it is a very brytel tree yealow within &amp; the yonge brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches which come ſtreyghte from the roote are al foure ſquare, wherfore ſome cal it Euonomum, I haue ſene it betwene Barkway and Ware in the hedges. It maye be called in engliſhe Spyndle tree or ſquare tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Eupatorium.</head>
               <p>Eupatorium named in greeke Eupato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion, is called in engliſh Agrunony, in duch Agrimonien, in frenche Aigremoine. Thys is not Eupatorium Meſues, for that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in engliſhe Maudlene. It is hote in the fyrſt degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Faba.</head>
               <p>Faba is named in greeke Cyainos, in en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gliſhe a beane, in duche Ein bou, in frenche
<pb facs="tcp:5227:26"/> Febue. Beanes growe in al cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre is in ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie inough.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Fagus.</head>
               <p>Fagus is named in greeke Phegos, in duch Ein buchbaume, in french Fan. Bech trees growe plentuouſly in many places of England. Two of the greateſt that euer I ſawe, growe at Morpeth on .ij. hylles right ouer the Caſtle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ferula.</head>
               <p>Ferula is called in greeke Narthex, but howe that it is named in engliſhe, as yet I can not tel, for I neuer ſawe it in Englande but in Germany in diuerſe places. It maye be named in engliſhe herbe Sagapene or Feuel gyante, it is hote and maketh ſuttle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ficus.</head>
               <p>Ficus is called in greke Syce, in engliſh a fig tree, in duch Ein fyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baume, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch vng figuer. There are diuers Fyg trees in Englande in gardines, but no where els.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ficus Aegyptia.</head>
               <p>Ficus Aegyptia is called alſo Morus Aegyptia and Sycomorus, it is one tree, ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyng a name of a Fyg tree and a Mulbery tree, wherefore it may be called a Mulbery fyg tree, it is to be found in Aegypt, but not in thys parte of Europa that I knowe of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Filix.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:26"/>
               <p>Filix is called in greeke Pieris, in engliſh a Ferne or a brake, in duche Ein walt farn, in frenche Fauchier. There are two kindes of brakes. The one kynde is called in latin Filix maſcula and in greeke Pteris, it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth communely vpon ſtones, it is al ful of litle wynges euen from the roote. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde kynde is called in greeke Thelypte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, in latine Filix femina, thys is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune Ferne or brake, whiche the Northerne men cal a bracon. It hath a long bare ſtalke and the leaues onely on the toppe of that.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Filicula.</head>
               <p>Filicula is called in greeke Polypodion, in ingliſhe Polipodium or walferne, in duche Engelſuet, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Polypody. It groweth in Oke trees, and in olde walles. It dryeth wythout bytyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Feniculum.</head>
               <p>Feniculum is called in greke Marathro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in engliſh Fenel or fenkel, in duch Fenchel, in french Fenoul. Fenel is hote in the thyrd degree and dry in the fyrſt. Feuel groweth in gardines in al countreis.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Fenum grecum.</head>
               <p>Fenum grecum is called in greeke Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, in engliſhe Fenegreeke, in duche Buhſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne, in frenche Fenecreke. It groweth in Italy, and in Germany. Fenegreke is hote
<pb facs="tcp:5227:27"/> in the ſeconde degree and dry in the fyrſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Fragraria.</head>
               <p>Fragraria is called in engliſh a ſtrawbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry leafe, whoſe fruite is called in engliſhe a ſtrawbery, in duche Erdeber, in frenche Frayſne. Euery man knoweth wel inough where ſtrawberies growe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Fraxinus.</head>
               <p>Fraxinus is called in greeke Melia, in engliſh an Aſhe tree, in duch an Aſhe baume in frenche Fraiſne. Aſſhes growe in euery countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Galion.</head>
               <p>Galion or gallion is named in engliſhe in the North countrey Maydens heire, in duch Be hſtrowe, in french Petit Muguet. It groweth muche in buſſhes and it is lyke Gooſgraſſe or gooſhareth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Galeopſis.</head>
               <p>Galeopſis after my iudgemente is the herbe, whiche is called in engliſhe red Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaungel. It is lyke Archaungel, but it hath a purple floure, and leſſe leaues and ſhorter. It groweth in hedges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Geniſta.</head>
               <p>Geniſta is named in engliſhe Broume, in duch Geniſt, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Dugenet. Broume groweth in al countreis of England, where as I haue ben. Geniſta is not Spartum, as
<pb facs="tcp:5227:27"/> I ſhall proue in my latine Herball.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Gentiana.</head>
               <p>Gentiana called in greeke Gentiane, is called in engliſhe Gentiane, in duche Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch de la entienne. It groweth much in the Alpes, and a baſterde kinde of it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in the middowes about Bon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Geranium.</head>
               <p>Geranium is of two kynd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. The one kynde is called Pinke nedle or Cranes byl, the other is called Pes columbinus of the commune Herbaries, and it maye be called in engliſhe Douefote.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Gethium.</head>
               <p>Gethium is called in engliſhe a Syue, a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chiue, or a ciuet, in duche Suitlauch, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Ciues &amp; cucions. Ciues growe only in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines that I know of, in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but a litle aboue Bon they growe in great plentie by the Rhene ſyde vnſet or ſowen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Geum.</head>
               <p>Geum is called in engliſhe Auennes, in duch Benedicte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kraut, in french Salmond. It is named of the herbaries Garyophylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Sanamunda and benedicta. It groweth communely about hedges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Gingidium.</head>
               <p>Gingidium except I be deceyued with a great ſort of learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is the herbe whiche
<pb facs="tcp:5227:28"/> is called in engliſhe Cheruel, in duche Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel oder korbel kraute, in frenche Cerfuile. Cheruel is called of ſome wryters Chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phillum, &amp; of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune ſorte Lerefolium.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Git.</head>
               <p>Git is named in greeke Melanthion, in engliſhe herbe Git or Nigella romana, in duche Schwartz kummich, in frenche Niel. It groweth in gardines onely that I haue ſene, ſauynge that in Germany there gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in the corne fieldes after the corne is caried away a certeyne kinde of Git which hath a good ſauour, &amp; is in al poyntes lyke the gardine Nigella, ſauynge that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles whiche holde the blacke ſeede are not al in one, as the other haue, and ſmelleth not ſo wel ful out, as the other do. It is hote &amp; dry in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Glaſtum.</head>
               <p>Glaſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called in greke Iſatis, in engliſh wad, &amp; not Ode as ſome corrupters of the engliſhe tonge do nikename it, in duch waid or weid, in french Gueſde. Wad is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Iuliker land, &amp; ſome is now ſet in England. The wild wad groweth ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuouſly in Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>many beſide the Rhene, &amp; in many corne fiel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des in hye Almany. Wyld wad is called in engliſhe aſhe of Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It dryeth muche.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Glaux,</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:28"/>
               <p>Glaux is very ſtraunge in Englande, for I neuer ſawe the ryghte Glaux in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, ſauing it that was brought out of Ita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by Iohn Falconer. It groweth in Flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by the ſea ſyde, as I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre .iij. myles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dunkyrke. It may be called in engliſhe ſea Trifoly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Glycyrrhiza.</head>
               <p>Glycyrrhiza called in latin Radix dulcis is named in engliſh Lycores, in duch Sueſz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holtz, or Lycoris or Clariſh, in frenche Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiſſe or Rigoliſſe. It groweth in the Roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of Germany wythout any ſettynge or ſowyng. It is warme and in a maner hote.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Goſſipium.</head>
               <p>Goſſipiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called of Barbarus wryters, Bombax and Cotonum, in engliſhe Coton in greeke Pylon, in duche Baumewoll, in frenche ducotton. I neuer ſawe it growyng ſauyng onely in Bonony.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Gramen.</head>
               <p>Gramen is called in greeke Agroſtis, in engliſh great graſſe, in duch, graſſe. Some take Stichwurt for the true graſſe, but they are deceyued. The beſt Gramen and moſte agreyng with Dioſcoridis deſcription, dyd I ſee in Germany with other maner of roo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, then the commune graſſe hath.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Halimus.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:29"/>
               <p>Halimus groweth plentuouſly in the Ilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of eaſt Freſelande where as the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters make verince of the red beries. I haue ſene it alſo in Flaunders by the ſea ſyde. It maye be called in engliſhe ſea wyllowe or prickwylowe becauſe it hath the leaues of a wylowe and prickes lyke a thorne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Heliotropium.</head>
               <p>Heliotropiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> called alſo ſcorpyuros gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth plentuouſly aboute Bonony. I haue had it growynge muche in my gardine in Germany. They are foully deceyued and ſhamefully deceyue other whiche holde in their wrytynges that our Marigold is He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liotropium Dioſcoridis. Heliotropium mai be called in engliſhe Scorpiones tayle. It is hote in the thyrde degree &amp; dry in the ſecond.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Helxine.</head>
               <p>Helxine or pardition is called in engliſhe Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etorie or Pelletorie of the wal, in duche ſaynt Peters kraut, or Tag vnd naught, in frenche Du parietaire. The Herbaries cal it Parietariam. It groweth on walles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Hieracium.</head>
               <p>Hiera cium is of two kyndes. The one is called in latin Hieracium magnum. It may be called in engliſhe greate Haukweede or yealowe Succory. It groweth in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny about Colo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The ſecond is like Dande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyon,
<pb facs="tcp:5227:29"/> it groweth in many myddowes in Germany. I thynke it maye be founde alſo in Englande. It maye be called in engliſhe leſſe Hauke weede.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Hippogloſſum.</head>
               <p>Hippogloſſum is called of the Poticaries and the Herbaries of Germany and Italy Vnularia, in duche Zaflinkrant. I haue not ſene it in England. It is called of ſome wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Laurus alixandrina. It maye be called in engliſh Tonge Laurel becauſe it hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leaues lyke tonges growyng out of the greater leafe, whiche is lyke a Laurel leafe. It is manifeſtly hote.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Hirundinaria.</head>
               <p>Hirundinaria called in greeke Chelido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, is of .ij. kyndes. The one kinde, that is the greater, is called in engliſh Sele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, in duch Schelwurtz, in frenche Theliddine or Eſclere. It groweth in hedges in the ſpring &amp; hath yealowe iuce. The ſecond kynde cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in latin Chelidonium minus, is called in engliſhe Fygwurte, it groweth vnder the ſhaddowes of aſhe trees. It is one of the fyrſt herbes that hath floures in the ſpring. Celendine is hote &amp; dry in the thyrd degree. Hixundinaria minor is hote in the fourth degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Hordeum.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:30"/>
               <p>Hordeum called in greeke Crithe, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe Barley, in duche Gerſt, in frenche Orge, it is of diuerſe kyndes. The fyrſte kinde is called in latin Hordeum diſtichum, in engliſhe Barley. The ſeconde kynde is called in latin Hordeum tetraſtichum, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe By Barley or beare, or byg alone. Thys kynde groweth muche in the North countrey. The thyrde kynde is called in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Hordeum Hexaſtichum, I haue not ſene thys kynde in Englande, but ofte tymes in high Germany, wherfore it maye be called in engliſhe duch Barley. The fourth kynde is called of Galene in the greeke tonge, Gymnochrithon, in latin Hordeum nudum of other ſome Hordeum mundum. It maye be called in engliſhe wheate Barley becauſe it hath no mo Huſkes on it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wheat hath. It groweth in Italy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Hordeum murinum.</head>
               <p>Hordeum murinum, whiche Plenie cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth alſo Phenicea ſemeth to be in Dioſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides Phenix, as touchynge the name, but in the thynge they ſeme ſomewhat to vary, for Phenicea or Hordeum murinum of Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, is the wal Barley, whiche groweth on mud walles. Phenix Dioſcoridis ſemeth to be the herbe which is called in Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brig ſhire Way bent. It is like vnto barlei in the eare</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:30"/>
               <head>Hyacinthus.</head>
               <p>Hyacinthus verus groweth plentuouſly in the mount Appe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nine. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune Hya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinthus is muche in Englande aboute Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Shene, and it is called in Engliſhe crowtoes, and in the North partes Craw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees. Some vſe the rootes for glue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Hyoſiris.</head>
               <p>Hyoſiris is a litle rough herbe like Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delyon, leſſe then litle Haukeweede. It gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in baron groundes &amp; in ſandy diches.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Hypericon.</head>
               <p>Hypericon is called of barbarus writers Fuga demonum, in engliſhe ſaynte Iohans wurte or ſaynt Iohans graſſe, in duch ſaynt Iohans kraute. It groweth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely in al places of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, &amp; eſpecially in woddes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Hiſſopus.</head>
               <p>Hiſſopus is called in engliſhe Hyſope, in duch Iſpe, in french Dehylope. Hyſope gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in gardines onely, in Englande as far as I haue ſene.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Iaſme.</head>
               <p>Iaſminu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwyſe called Iaſme, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in engliſhe Gethſamyne, in frenche Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemin. It groweth communely in gardines about London.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Iberis.</head>
               <p>Iberis otherwyſe named Kardamantike
<pb facs="tcp:5227:31"/> groweth plentuouſly in Germany aboute Bon where as it is called Beſemkraute. It groweth in great plentie in eaſt Freſelande aboute the ſea bankes. Fuchſius taketh the herbe which I take for Iberis, to be Thla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpi ſecundum.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Intubus.</head>
               <p>Intubus whiche is named in greeke Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, is of two ſortes. The one is called Intu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus hortenſis, and the other is called Inty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſylueſtris. Intybus hortenſis is of two ſortes, the one is called Endyue, or whyte Eudyue, &amp; the other is called gardine Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cory. Intybus ſylueſtris is of two ſortes, the one is called in latin Cichorium, and in engliſhe Succory or hardewes, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is called of Theophraſtus Aphaca, of Plinie Hedypnois, in engliſhe Dan de lyon or prieſtes crowne, in duche Pfaffenblat, it groweth euery where. Theſe kyndes are colde and dry about the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Inula</head>
               <p>Inula is called in greeke Helenion, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe Alecampane, or Elecampane, in duch Alantz wurtz, in frenche, and in the Potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhopped Enula ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pana. It is hote and dry in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Irio.</head>
               <p>Irio is named in greeke Eriſimo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe
<pb facs="tcp:5227:31"/> wynter creſſe, it groweth about tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and aboute water ſydes, but not where as the water cometh, as watercreſſe doeth. The Coloners cal this herbe winter cerſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Inglans.</head>
               <p>Inglans called alſo Nux regia, &amp; in greke Carya Baſilica is called in engliſh a Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut tree, in duche Em noſz baume, in french Vng noier.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Iuncus odoratus.</head>
               <p>Iuncus odoratus ſiue rotundus, is called in greeke Schenos, in engliſhe ſquinant, in duche Kamelhewe, in the Poticaries ſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes Squinantum. It is meaſurably hote &amp; byndynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Iuniperus.</head>
               <p>Iuniperus is called in greke Arcenthus, in engliſhe ieneper or iuniper, in duche Rek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holterbaume, in frenche Geneure. It gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth muche in Germany and in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Englande alſo. It is hote and drye in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Labruſca.</head>
               <p>Labruſca whiche is called in greeke Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelos agria or Omphax, is of two ſortes, the one kynde is ſo wylde that it hath onely floures and goeth no further, and thys is called Ena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>the. The other hath floures and alſo litle grapes. I haue ſene of both the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:5227:32"/> ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuouſly in Italy in diuerſe places, by the floude Padus, and in highe Almany al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. It may be called in engliſhe a wild vine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lactuca.</head>
               <p>Lactuca called in greeke Thridax, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe Lettis, in duch Lattich, in french Vng laictue, is of diuerſe ſortes. One is called in latin Lactuca capitata, and in engliſh Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bage lettis, an other is called in latin Lactu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca ſeſſilis, in engliſhe ſpredynge Lettis. The thyrde ſorte is called in latin Lactuca ſylue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, in engliſhe grene Endyue, the Potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries haue longe abuſed thys herbe for right Endyue, but they haue bene deceyued. It is meaſurably colde and moyſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lagopus</head>
               <p>Lagopus called alſo Logopyros gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth much amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the corne, it hath a rough toppe lyke Doune, and leaues lyke a Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, wherfore it maye be named in engliſhe rough Trifoly or harefote, the duch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal it. Katzenklee, the french men Pede de leure. It dryeth manifeſtly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lamium.</head>
               <p>Lamium called alſo Vrtica iners and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonium, is named in engliſhe dead nettle or whyte nettle, in duche Weiſzueſlen, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Ortie morte, it groweth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in hedges</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lampſana.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:32"/>
               <p>Lampſana Plinij, ſemeth to be the weede that we cal communely in engliſhe wylde Cole, and in other places Carlocke, it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely amonge the corne. Dioſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides deſcribeth one wyth ſmouther leaues whiche I haue ſene in Bonony and in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Larix.</head>
               <p>Larix or larex groweth in the higheſt top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of the Alpes higher then the fyrres do, the duch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal Laricem ein larchen baume, the frenche men cal it Vularge. It maye be called in engliſhe a Larche tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Laſerpitium gallicum.</head>
               <p>Laſerpitium gallicum as Ruellius iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, is the herbe called of the Herbaries Angelica, but I rather holde wyth Fuchſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us whiche ſayeth that the herbe, whiche en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal Pillitorie of Spayne, the duch men Meiſterwurtz, the Herbaries Oſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium and magiſtrancia, is Laſerpitium gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licum, for the leaues of it are lyker vnto Perſeley.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lathyris.</head>
               <p>Lathyris is called in engliſhe commune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spourge, in duch Sprynkorner, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Eſpurge. It is called of ſome Eſula maior. Thys kynde of Spurge hath ſwete ſeedes as witnes Dioſcorides and Plinie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:33"/>
               <head>Lauer.</head>
               <p>Lauer or Sion is called of ſome engliſhe men Bellragges, of other ſome yealowe watercreſſes. Howe be it there is an other herbe lyke Rocket whiche groweth in the waters and brokes, which is the ryght wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercreſſe. Yealowe water creſſe groweth in water ſydes and in ſprynges &amp; wel heades.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Laurus.</head>
               <p>Laurus is called in engliſhe a Baye tree, or a Laurel tree, in greeke Daphne, in duche a Lorber baume, in french Vnglaurier. Bay trees are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune in gardines in the South parte of Englande, but they are very ſkarſe in Germany. It is vehemently hote &amp; drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lens.</head>
               <p>Lens is named in greeke Phacos, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe Lentil, in duche Liuſes, in french Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tille. Lentilles are ſowen in corne fieldes and growe as Tares do.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lens paluſtris.</head>
               <p>Lens paluſtris called in greeke Phacos epiton telmato<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is called in engliſh Duckes meate or water Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ulles, in duch waſſer liuſe</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lentiſeus</head>
               <p>Lentiſcus is called in greeke Schinos, in duche Maſtix baume, in frenche Lentiſque, I neuer ſawe it ſanynge onely in Italy. It maye be called in engliſhe Maſtike tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:33"/>
               <head>Lepidium.</head>
               <p>Lepidium is wel knowen in Englande and is called wyth a falſe name Dittany, duche men cal it Pfefferkraut, it groweth in Morpeth in Northumberlande by a water called Wanſpeke in great ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie alone with out any ſettyng or ſowyng. It is hote in the fourth degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Libanotis.</head>
               <p>Libanotis called in latin Roſmarinus is of .iij. kyndes, where we haue none ſauyng only Roſmarinum Coronarium, which we cal in engliſhe Roſmary, whiche groweth plentuouſly in gardines in Englande. It is hote in the ſeconde and dry in the fyrſt.</p>
               <p>Lichen is called in engliſe Liuerwurte, in duch Steinliberkraut, in french Hepatique, the Poticaries cal it Hepatica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It groweth vpon ſtones and moyſt groundes, &amp; where as the ſunne cometh not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Liguſticum.</head>
               <p>Liguſticum or Libyſticum groweth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in England nor Germany that euer I could ſee or heare tel of. I haue ſene it in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly, but no where els. It maye be called in engliſhe Lumbardy Louage, it is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hote.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Liguſtrum.</head>
               <p>Liguſtrum is called in greke Cypros, in
<pb facs="tcp:5227:34"/> engliſhe Prim print or Priuet, though Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ote more holdely then lernedly, defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the contrary as I ſhal proue in my latin herbal when it ſhal be ſet fourth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lilium.</head>
               <p>Lilium is named in greke Crinon, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe a Lily, in duche Ein gilgen, in french Vng Lis.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Limonium.</head>
               <p>Limonium named of the Herbaries Vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rola, is named in duch wintergrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth in woddes in Germany in great ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and in an Iland of eaſt Freſeland called Nordeney. It maye he called in engliſhe wyntergreue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Linum.</head>
               <p>Linum is called in engliſhe Flax, lyne or lynte, in duche Flachs, in frenche du lyne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lithoſpermon.</head>
               <p>Lithoſpermon is called of the Herbaries M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſolis, in engliſhe Grummel, but it ſhoulde be called Gray myle, in duch ſteen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in frenche Gre myl. It groweth ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly aboute woddes and buſſhes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lolium.</head>
               <p>Lolium is named in greke Ara, in engliſh Darnel, in duch Kaweitze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Lulch, or dort in frce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>h Some take cockel for lolio, but thei are far deceyued as I ſhal declare at large
<pb facs="tcp:5227:34"/> if God wil, in my latin herbal. Darnel gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth amonge the corne and the corne goeth out of kynde into Darnel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lotus vrbana.</head>
               <p>Lotus vrbana called in greeke Lotos emeros is not growynge in Englande that euer I could ſpie. It groweth in Ferraria in the blacke friers gardine, and in claue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na, it is lyke cuckowes meate, but that it hath a yealow floure. It may be named in engliſh gardine Clauer or gardine Trifoly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lotus ſylueſtris.</head>
               <p>Lotus ſylueſtris is called in greke Lotus agrios, in duche ſtund kraute, in Freſeland, wyt Nardus. It groweth muche in eaſt Freſelande in gardines, of thys kynde are the herbes whiche are callad here in engliſh Melilotes. Thys herbe groweth nowe in Syon gardine. It maye be called in engliſh wylde lote.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lupus ſalictarius.</head>
               <p>Lupus ſalictarius is named in greeke Bryon, in engliſhe hoppes, in duche hopten in frenche Hupelon. Hoppes do growe by hedges and buſſnes both ſet and baſet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lycopſis.</head>
               <p>Lycopſis Dioſcoridis ſemeth to be vnto Ruellius, and to diuerſe other learned men Lynagloſſa, of the Poticaries which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:5227:35"/> in engliſhe Houndes tonge, &amp; after my iudgemente the deſcription in al poyntes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth wel ſauyng that there is no mention made of the burres in the toppes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lycopus.</head>
               <p>Lycopus is called of the commune Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baxies Cardiaca, in engliſhe Motherwurt, in duche Hertzgeſpan, in frenche Agri pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. It groweth in hedges &amp; about walles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lyſimachia.</head>
               <p>Lyſimachia is of two ſortes. The one is deſcribed of Dioſcorides, and it hath a yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe floure. Some cal it Lycimachiam lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>team, it groweth by the Temes ſyde beſide Shene, it may be called in engliſhe yealow Louſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ryfe or herbe Wylowe. The other kynde is deſcribed of Plinie, and it is called Lyſimachia purpurea, it groweth by water ſydes, alſo and maye be called in engliſhe red looſſtryfe, or purple loſeſtryfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Malua.</head>
               <p>Malua is called in greeke Malache, in engliſhe a Mallowe or a Mallo. Malua is deuided into Maluam hortenſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſtrem. Malua horte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſis is of two kindes. The one is called alone in greeke Malache in engliſhe Holyhoke, and of thys ſort is the iagged mallowe. The other kynde as Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſayeth is called in greeke Molloche, or
<pb facs="tcp:5227:35"/> malope, it is called in engliſhe french Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe. Malua ſylueſtris is of .ij. ſortes. The one is called in latin Malua ſylueliris, in greeke Malache Cherſaia, in Engliſhe a wylde Mallowe, in duche Halen pappel, in frenche Malue ſauage. The other kynde is called of Dioſcorides Althea &amp; Hibiſcus, of Plinie Ariſtalthea, of Galene Anaden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, of Etius Deudromalache, in engliſhe marriſhe Mallowe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Mandragoras.</head>
               <p>Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dragoras is called in engliſh a Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drage, Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drag<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is wel knowen in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; it groweth in diuerſe gardines. The duch men cal it Alram. Maudrage is colde in the thyrde degree, but the Apples haue ſome heate in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Marrubium.</head>
               <p>Marrubium is called in greeke Praſion, in engliſhe Horehound, in duch Weſen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn, in french Du marrubium, it groweth aboute townes and villages. It is hote in the ſeconde degree and dry in the thyrde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Medica.</head>
               <p>I haue not ſene Medica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> growe in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, wherfore I knowe no engliſhe name that it hath. It hath leaues like a clauer and horned cods wherin it hath ſede ſomthing facioned lyke Fenegreekt. Therfore it maye be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:5227:36"/> in engliſhe horned Clauer or ſnail Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foly becauſe the coddes are ſo wrythen in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne as a water ſnayle or ſaynte corniliu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſes horne. It groweth in many places of Italy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Malus.</head>
               <p>Malus is named in greke Melea, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe an Apple tree, in duche Eiu Opfel bauine, in frenche vn pommier.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Malus medica.</head>
               <p>Malus medica otherwiſe called Malus Aſſyria, or Citrus is called an Orenge tree and vnder the name of Citrus are contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned both Limoues &amp; alſo Lytrones &amp; Ore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Theſe trees grow in Spayne &amp; Italy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Malus Cotonea.</head>
               <p>Malus Cotonea is called in greeke Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lea Cydonios, in engliſhe a Quince tree, in duch Kutte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baume or ein quidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baume, in frenche Vn Coignier.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Malus Perſica.</head>
               <p>Malus perſica is called in greeke Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lea Perſice, in engliſhe a Peche tree, in duch Ein pferſike baume, in french vn Perchier.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Malus punica.</head>
               <p>Malus Punica is called in greeke Roia in engliſhe a Pomgranat tree, in duche Em Graunat baume, in french Vng Pomier des granades, Pomgarnat trees growe plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly
<pb facs="tcp:5227:36"/> in Italy and in Spayne, and there are certayne in my Lordes gardine at Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but their fruite cometh neuer vnto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. The poticaries cal the fruite of this tree Pomum granatum.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Malus armeniaca.</head>
               <p>Malus armeniaca is called in Greeke, Melea armeniace, in highe duche Land ein amarel baume, in the dioſes of Colo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kardu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melker baume, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Vng abricottier, and ſome engliſhe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal the fruite an Abricok. Me thynke ſeinge that we haue very fewe of theſe trees as yet, it were better to cal it, an haſty Peche tree becauſe it is lyke a pech and it is a great whyle rype before the pech trees, wherfore the fruite of thys tree is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led malum precox. There are in Colo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great plentie of haſty peche trees.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Melfrugum.</head>
               <p>Melfrugum named in greeke Meleas, ſitos groweth muche in Germany beſyde Bon, and that alwayes amonge the corne it is very lyke the commune Melilote, but that it hath whyte floures. It maye be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in engliſhe whyte melilote.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Meutha.</head>
               <p>Meutha is called in greeke Edioſmos, in engliſhe Mynte, in duche muntzen, in french dela ment. Mynt is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inough in
<pb facs="tcp:5227:37"/> al countreis. Mynte is hote in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Menthaſtrum.</head>
               <p>Menthaſtrum is called in greeke Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſmos agrios, in engliſhe wylde mynte, it groweth in watery places wyth a rounde leafe &amp; thycke with a longe eare in the top.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Mercurialis.</head>
               <p>Mercurialis is called in greeke Ermou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poa or Linozoſtis, in engliſhe Mercury, in duche Recroute and Bingelkraute, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch mercuriallo. The herbe whiche is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called in engliſhe mercury hath nothyng to do wyth mercurialis, whereof I ſpake nowe. Let the Poticaries vſe thys mercury and let the commune mercury alone. Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury is as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune about Colon in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, as any weede is commune in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines in England. It is hote and dry in the fyrſte degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Meſpilus.</head>
               <p>Meſpilus called in greeke meſpile, is of two ſortes, the one hath three ſtones in the fruite, and that kynde is not wyth vs. The other kynde hath in the fruite, fyue ſtones, and thys kynde is commune in Englande, and it is called in englſhe a medler tree or an open ars tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Meum.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:37"/>
               <p>Meum called of the grecians Meon and Meion is called of the Poticaries Men, in duch Bearwurtz. Some Poticaries in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe vſe thys herbe for Pencedano and ſo they cal it. I neuer ſawe this herbe in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande ſauynge once at ſayute Oſwarldes where as the inhabiters called it Speknel, it groweth in greate plentie eighte myle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Bon in a fielde beſyde Slyde in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many. It maye be called in engliſhe mewe or duche Dyl. The rootes are hote in the thyrde degree and dry in the ſeconde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Milium.</head>
               <p>Milium is called in greeke Cegchros, &amp; Piſton, in duche Hirſz, in french Du millet. I haue not ſene it in Englande, but very muche in high Germany. It maye be called in engliſhe Hirſe or millet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Milium indicum,</head>
               <p>Milium indicum is nowe muche ſowen in Italy, and it is in ſome gardines in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many where as it is called turkiſhe corne, and ſome cal it in Englande wheate of tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key. Howe be it there is an other thynge that is the true turkiſh wheate, it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to cal it after my iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t turkiſh millet</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Morus.</head>
               <p>Morus is called in greeke morea, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh a mulbery tree, in duch maulberbaum
<pb facs="tcp:5227:38"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> dines in Englande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Myrica.</head>
               <p>Myrica, otherwyſe named tamarix, and of the Herbaries Tamariſcus is named in duche tamariſke, in frenche tameris. I dyd neuer ſee thys tree in Englande, but ofte in high Germany, and in Italy. The Potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Colon before I gaue them warning vſed for thys, the bowes of vghe, &amp; the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaries of London vſe nowe for thys quik tree, the ſcholemaiſters in Englanoe haue of longe tyme called myrica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heath, or lyng, but ſo longe haue they bene deceyued al to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. It maye be called in engliſhe, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marik.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Myrrhis.</head>
               <p>Myrrhis is called in Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bryge ſhyre ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſhes, in other places mockecheruel, in duche wilder Peterlin, in frenche Perſil de aſne. It groweth in hedges in euery countrey, but the beſt that euer I ſawe was in Germany beſyde Bon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Myrtus.</head>
               <p>Myrtus is called in greeke myrrine, in engliſh a myrtle tree, or a myrt tree, in frech meurte. Myrt trees growe in great plentie in Italy in the mount Appenine beſide Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ony. Some al uſe a litle ſhrub called Gal
<pb facs="tcp:5227:38"/> in engliſhe, whiche groweth in fennes and wateriſh mores formyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, but they are far deceyued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Napus.</head>
               <p>Napus is named in greeke Bounias, in duche Stekruben, in french Ranonet or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueau, I haue hearde ſome cal it in engliſhe a turnepe, and other ſome a naued or a nauet, it maye be called alſo longe Rape or nauet gentle, as a rape hath a round roote, ſo hath a nauet a longe roote and ſomthynge yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowiſhe. Thys herbe groweth plentuouſly at Andernake in Germany.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Narciſſus.</head>
               <p>Narciſſus is of diuerſe ſortes. There is one wyth a purple floure, whiche I neuer ſawe, &amp; an other wyth a white floure, which groweth ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuouſly in my Lordes gardine in Syon, and it is called of diuerſe, whyte Laus tibi, it maye be called alſo whyte da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffadyl. Plenie maketh mention of a kynde called Narciſſus herbaceus, whiche is after my iudgement our yealowe daſfodyl.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Nardus.</head>
               <p>Nardus is named in greeke Nardos, in engliſhe Spykuarde, the Potecaries name it Spicam Nardi, it groweth not in Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa that I haue heard tel of. It is hote in the fyrſt degree and dry in the ſeconde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:39"/>
               <head>Nardus celtica.</head>
               <p>Nardus celtica, otherwyſe called Sali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unca, is in great plentie growyng in the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. The Germanes cal it mariend magda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lene kraut, it may be called in engliſhe fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch ſpiknarde, when the indiſh ſpiknard is olde and duſty and rotten, it is better to vſe thys in medicines then it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Naſturtium.</head>
               <p>Naſturtium is called in greeke Carda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, in engliſhe Creſſe or Kerſe, in duche Creſſich, in frenche Creſſon, Aleuois, and naſitorte. Creſſes growe no where, but in gardines. It is drye and hote in the fourth degree after Auerrois.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Nerion.</head>
               <p>Nerion otherwyſe called Rhododendro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and Rhododaphne, is named in duch Oſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in frenche Roſage. I neuer ſawe it but in Italy. It maye be called in engliſhe Roſe bay tree or roſe Laurel. This tree is named of ſome oleander.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Nux caſtanea.</head>
               <p>Nux caſtanea is called in greeke Caſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, in engliſhe a Cheſnut tree, in duch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch, Ong Chaſtagne. Cheſnuttes growe in diuerſe places of Englande. The manieſt that I haue ſene was in Kent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Nymphea.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:39"/>
               <p>Nymphea is alſo named in greeke nym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaia, &amp; madonais &amp; is called in engliſh wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter Roſes, &amp; ſome wyth the Poticaries cal it nenufar. The duch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal thys herbe See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blumen. Boeth the kyndes of water Roſes growe in ſtandyng waters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ocymum.</head>
               <p>Ocymum is called in engliſhe Baſyl, in duche Baſilien, in frenche du baſilike, the Poticaries cal it Baſilicon. It groweth in Englande onely in gardines. It is hote in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Oenanthe.</head>
               <p>Oenanthe is called boeth of the Herba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and of al our countrey men Filipendu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, in duch Rotenſteynbrech. Some ſay that the ſame herbe is called Phellandryon in Plinie. Filipendula groweth in great plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie beſide Syon &amp; Shene in the middowes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Olea.</head>
               <p>Olea or oliua is called in greeke Elaia, in engliſhe an Olyue tree, in duche Ein ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banine, in french Ong oliuerier. Oliue trees growe plentuouſly in Italy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Olus atrum.</head>
               <p>Olus atrum is called in greeke Hypoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linon, in engliſh Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, in duch ſchwartz, Peterſily or groſſe eppich, in frenche mei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry. Some poticaries though
<pb facs="tcp:5227:40"/> falſly, cal it Petroſelinum macedonicum.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Opulus.</head>
               <p>Opulus is a tree commune in Italy &amp; Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>many, but I haue not ſene it that I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre in Englande. It is called in frenche as Geſnere ſayeth opier, and ſo maye it be alſo called in engliſh tyl we fynde a better name</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Origanum.</head>
               <p>Origanum is called in engliſhe organ, howe be it I neuer ſawe the trewe organ in England. I haue ſene diuerſe times organe whiche grewe in Candy, muche hotter then thys our commune organ is, whiche is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led origanum ſylueſtre in latin, and in ſome places of England wylde mergerum. It is hote and dry in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Orminum.</head>
               <p>Orminum is called in engliſh Clarie, in duche Scharlach, in french ornali, howe be it the deſcription of Dioſcorides doeth not in al poyntes agree, ſome cal thys herbe ſclarea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Orminu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſylueſtre is ſuppoſed to be the herbe, which is called oculus Chriſti.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ornithigalum.</head>
               <p>Ornithigalon is called in Colon Hondes vllich, but I can not tel howe that it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in engliſhe, for I neuer ſawe it in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, ſauyng onely beſyde Sheue herde by the Temmes ſyde, howe be it after the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowynge
<pb facs="tcp:5227:40"/> of the duche tonge it maye be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led dogleke or dogges onion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Orobauche.</head>
               <p>Orobanche is ſo rare an herbe in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, that I neuer ſawe it in al Englande, but in Northumberlande, where as it was called newe chappel ſloure. It may be of his propertie called Chokeweede, becauſe it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth and choketh the herbes that it ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and claſpeth wyth his roote. It is colde and dry in the fyrſt degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Oryza.</head>
               <p>Oryza is called in engliſh Ryſe, in duch and french ryze. Ryſe groweth plentuouſly in watery myddowes betwene Myllane and Pauia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Oſyris.</head>
               <p>Oſyris or oſyrias groweth plentuouſly in Englande, but I do not remembre what name it hath. If it haue no name it maye be called in engliſhe Lynary or todes flax, for the Poticaries cal it Linaciam, and the duch cal it Krotenflaks.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Oxyacantha.</head>
               <p>Oxyacantha is called in engliſhe as it is named of the poticaries berberes. Of ſome, pipriges, in duch Santich, in frenche Eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neniuet, or de Berberis. Berberies growe wylde in the hedges and woddes in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,
<pb facs="tcp:5227:41"/> but in Englande onely in gardines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Oxyphenix.</head>
               <p>Oxyphenix is called of the Poticaries Tamarindus, and it maye be called in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe a tamarinde. I neuer ſawe the tree it ſelfe, but the fruite alone. It is colde in the thyrde and dry in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Oxys.</head>
               <p>Oxys is called in engliſh Allelua, Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kowes meate, and wod ſorel, in duche Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen ampfer, in frenche payne de Coquu. It groweth in woddes aboute tree rootes and amonge buſſhes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Peonia.</head>
               <p>Peonia is alſo named in greeke Glicyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, it is called in engliſhe peony or pyony, in duch peonienroſe, in french penoiſne and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noine. Peony the female groweth in euery countrey, but I neuer ſawe the male ſauing only in Anwerp. Peony roote is hote in the fyrſt and dry in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Palma.</head>
               <p>Palma is called in greeke phenix, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh a Date tree, in duch Ein dattel baume in french Vng arbri dict palme. I neuer ſaw any perfit date tree yet, but onely a litle one that neuer came to perfection. Date trees growe in Aſia in great plentie, but none in Europa, whiche brynge furth any fruite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:41"/>
               <head>Panicum.</head>
               <p>Panicum is called in greeke Elymos or melinos, in duche Fenike, in french paniz. I haue not ſene it in Englande, ſauyng in my Lordes gardine a Syon, but it may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Panike, it groweth in Italy and in high Almany in the fieldes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Papauer.</head>
               <p>Papauer is called in greeke Mecon, in engliſhe Poppy or Cheſboul, in duch m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom or manſom, in french du pauot. It gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth ſowen in gardines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Papauer erraticum.</head>
               <p>Papauer erraticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called in greeke Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas, in engliſhe Redcornroſe or wylde popy, in duche wilde man, korne roſen, or klapper roſen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Papauer corniculatum.</head>
               <p>Papauer corniculatum is called in greke mecoon ceratites, in engliſhe horned poppy or yealow poppy, in duch Gaelma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in Douer clyffes, and in many other places by the ſea ſyde. It is cold in the furth degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Papyros.</head>
               <p>Papyrus groweth not in Englande, it hath the facion of a greate Docke. I haue ſene it diuerſetymes in Anwerp, wherein was ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and of uerſe other marchaundiſe wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.
<pb facs="tcp:5227:42"/> It maye be called in engliſhe water pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or herbe paper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Parthenium.</head>
               <p>Parthenium after the mynde of Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus, Ruellius and diuerſe other lerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is the herbe which is called in barbarus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Matricaria, in engliſh feuerfew, in duch Mater, whoſe iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I rather alowe in this matter, then the iudgement of Fuchſius whiche would Parthenium to be ſtynkyng maydweede.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Paſtinaca.</head>
               <p>Paſtinaca is called in greke Staphilinos in engliſhe a Carot, in duche paſteney, in frenche Cariottes. Carettes growe in al countreis in plentie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Peplis.</head>
               <p>Peplis groweth by the ſea ſyde, not far from Venice. It is very like vnto wartwort but that it is ſhorter, thicker and ſpred vpon the grounde. It may be be called in engliſh ſea wartwurt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Peplum.</head>
               <p>I neuer ſawe peplum but once in Bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, it had litle ſmal leaues lyke tyme, and in other facion lyke ſpourge, wherfore it may be called ſpourge tyme in engliſhe, tyl we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fynde a better name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Periclymenum.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:42"/>
               <p>Periclymenum is called of the herbaries and poticaries Caprifolium and Matriſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, in engliſh wod bynde and Honyſuccles, in duch walt gylge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Cheure fuelle. Wodbyne, is commune in euery wodde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Perſonata.</head>
               <p>Perſonata is called in greeke Arceion or proſopion, in engliſh a Bur, in duche groſſe kletten, in frenche Glerteron or Gluteron. The Herbaries cal it Lappam maiorem. It groweth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly about townes &amp; villages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Pecaſites.</head>
               <p>Petaſites is called in the South partes of Englande a Butter bur, in the North, it is called about Morpeth Eldeus, the duch cal it peſtilentz krante. It groweth in broke ſydes and in moyſte middowes whiche are ouerflowen ſome tyme wyth the water. It dryeth in the thyrde degre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Petroſelinum.</head>
               <p>Petroſelinum named in latine Apium ſaxatile is not our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune perſely, as many haue beleued, but it is an other herbe, as I do thynke, whiche is called in ſome places of Italy Imperatoria. Whiche may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in engliſhe ſtone perſely or Lumberdy perſely. I neuer ſawe it in England neither in Germany, ſauynge onely dry, I proued ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Germany, but I coulde neuer make
<pb facs="tcp:5227:43"/> the ſeede growe there. For lacke of thys me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye vſe the ſeede of pilletory of Spayne called maſterwurt, or the ſeede of Angelica. Stone perſeley hath ſeede hote and drye in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Peucedanum.</head>
               <p>Peucedanum is called in duch harſtrang it groweth plentuouſly in Germany beſide Erenſfielde ouer agaynſte Byng, and alſo in the middowes beſide Mence, called other wyſe Maguncia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Phalaris,</head>
               <p>Phalaris is founde in many places of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly. It hath ſeede like Panicum, wherfore it maye be called in engliſhe petie panicke, or becauſe it is partly lyke graſſe and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lyke corne, it maye be called graſſe corne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Phaſiolus.</head>
               <p>Phaſiolus otherwyſe called Dolichos, maye be called in engliſhe longe peaſen or faſelles, in duche it is called Welſhe bonem or faeſelen, in frenche phaſeoles. Faſelles grow in great ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie in Italy about Pauia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Phu.</head>
               <p>Phu is called in engliſhe ſetwal, of other ſome Capones tayle, in duche Garten bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driane, in frenche Vertentrete. The potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in Germany cal it Valerianam. There are two other kyndes of Valeriane beſyde
<pb facs="tcp:5227:43"/> thys. Of the whiche, the one is growing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout water ſides, and in the moyſt plaſſhes and in moriſh groundes, and it is called in engliſhe wylde Valerian. The other kynde is called Valeriana greca, and thys is oure commune Valerian that we vſe agaynſte cuties wyth a blewe floure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Phyllitis.</head>
               <p>Phyllitis as Cordus iudgeth, is the herbe whiche we cal in engliſhe Hartes tonge, the duch cal Hirtze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> zuinge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the french me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lang de Cerfe, the poticaries Lingua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ceruinam. To whoſe iudgemente I rather aſſent, then to Ruellius &amp; Fuchſius. Hartes tonge gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in welles and olde walles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Picea.</head>
               <p>Picea is called in greeke as Theodore Gaza turneth, pitys, &amp; after Ruellius pence and it is called in duch rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dan, wherfore it maye be called in engliſhe a red fure tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Pinus.</head>
               <p>Pinus as Theodore tranſlateth, is called in greeke Pence, in engliſhe a pyne tree, in duch Ein forthen, in french Vng pin. Pines growe fayreſt in gardines. There groweth one fayre one in Richmund Pine nuttes are hote and dry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Piperitis.</head>
               <p>Piperitis called alſo Siliquaſtrum after
<pb facs="tcp:5227:44"/> the iudgemente of Fuchſius is the Herbe whiche is called in engliſhe Indiſhe peper, in duche indiſſhouer pfefer. If thys herbe be not it that it is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for, the yealow ſeedes whiche nughte to be whyte do onely hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The herbe groweth in certeyne gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines in Englande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Piſtacia.</head>
               <p>Piſtacia are called of the poticaries Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica, they may be called in engliſh Fiſtikes or Feſtike nuttes. I neuer ſawe the Fiſtike tre ſauing only in Bonony, the leaues were ſomthyng rounde and ful of red ſpottes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Piſum.</head>
               <p>Piſum is called in greeke Lecithos, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh a peaſe, in duch Erbes, or Erwiten, in frenche Puis. They growe communely in the fieldes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Pityuſa.</head>
               <p>Pityuſa is called of ſome Herbaries E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſula minor, and in engliſhe Spourge, but it oughte to be called litle Spourge, or Lint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpourge, for it hath ſmal leaues like Flax, or an other herbe called Linaria, whereby the one is ofte taken for the other, but the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is knowen by thys verſe. Eſula lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſcit, Linaria lac dare neſcit. The other kinde of this whiche groweth almoſte into the heighte of a ſmal tree, groweth a myle
<pb facs="tcp:5227:44"/> beneth Colon in a watery cloſſe whiche is ofte ouerflowen wyth the Rhene. It maye be called in engliſhe, Spourge gyant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Plantago.</head>
               <p>Plantago is called in greeke Arnoglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſos. There are two ſortes of Plantaginis, the one is called in engliſhe alone Plantaine or waybread, or great waybread. The other is called Rybwurte, or Rybgraſſe, and of ſome Herbaries Lancea lata. They are cold and dry in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Platanus.</head>
               <p>Platanus is called in engliſhe a playne tree, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch playne. I neuer ſaw any plaine tree in Englande ſauing once in Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlande beſyde Morpeth, and an other at Barnwel Abbay beſyde Cambryge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Polium.</head>
               <p>I haue ſene Polium of two ſortes, the one had hore leaues with the figure of time, and the other had leaues lyke wyld Tyme, but they were a greate dele lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Polium maye be called in engliſhe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The fyrſt kynde dyd I ſee in Italy. The ſecond in the Alpes of Rhetia beſide Cure. It is hote in the ſecond and dry in the third.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Polygonatum.</head>
               <p>Polygonatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called of Herbaries Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillum Solomonis, in engliſhe Scala celi,
<pb facs="tcp:5227:45"/> in duch wiſz wuriz. It maye be called in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe white wurte, it groweth plentuouſly in the woddes of Germany, but I neuer ſawe it out of a gardine in Englande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Polygonum</head>
               <p>Polygonum is called in latine Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria. There are two kindes of Polygonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the former kinde is called in engliſhe knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graſſe, or ſwyne graſſe, in duche Weggraſz wegorat or wegtede, in frenche de la corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e. The ſeconde kynde, whiche is called Polygonum femina is called in Engliſhe thycke Shanegraſſe, or ſhort Shaue graſſe. The firſte kynde groweth in highe wayes, the ſeconde kynde groweth in many places by water ſides, &amp; ſome time amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the corne. Knotgraſſe is colde in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Populus.</head>
               <p>Populus is of two kyndes, the fyrſte kynde is called in greeke Leuce, in latin Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus alba, in engliſhe whyte Popler or white Eſptree, in duch wiſz ſarbach. Thys kynde is cummune about the bankes of the floude Padus. The ſeconde kynde is called in greeke Aigeiros, in engliſhe alone, a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler, or an Aſp tree, or a blacke popler.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Porrum.</head>
               <p>Porrum is named in greke praſon, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe a Leke, in duche Ein lauch, in frenche
<pb facs="tcp:5227:45"/> Vng porrean. Beſyde the commune Leke there are two other kyndes, the one is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in latine porrum ſectinum, in engliſhe a frenche Leke. The other kynde is called in greeke Ampelo praſon, in latine porrum ſylueſtre, in duch wyld Lanch. I neuer ſawe thys kynde but in certeyne cloſes in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many aboute Bon. Lekes are hote in the fourth degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Potamogeton.</head>
               <p>Potamogeton is called in duche Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>krante, it maye be named in engliſhe Pond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantayne, or ſwymmynge plantayne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſwymmeth aboue pondes and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng waters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Portualca.</head>
               <p>Portulaca is called in engliſh purcellaine, in greeke Andrachne, in duch Burgel gren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and in neither land purcellane, in french porcellina.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Prunus.</head>
               <p>Prunus is called in greeke Coccimelea, in engliſhe a plum tree, in duche empſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men baume, in frenche Vun prunier. Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſylueſtris is called in engliſh a ſlo tree, or a ſle tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Pſyllium.</head>
               <p>Pſyllium is called in duch pſilien kraut, in french herbe puces or herbe a pulce, it gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth
<pb facs="tcp:5227:46"/> plentuouſly in Italy and in certeyne gardines in Germany. It may be called in engliſhe Flewurte. Flewurt is colde in the ſeconde degree, and is in a meane tempre in dryinge and moyſt makyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Pulegium.</head>
               <p>Pulegium is called in greeke Glechoon, in engliſhe Penyryal or puddyng graſſe, in duche poley, in french du pouliote. Peny ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al groweth in ſuche diches and watery pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as are ful of water in wynter, and are dyred vp in the begynnyng of Summer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Pyrus.</head>
               <p>Pyrus is called in greeke Apios, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe a Peare tree, in duche ein byrbaume, in frenche Vng poyrier.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Quercus.</head>
               <p>Quercus is named in greeke Drys, in engliſh an Oke or an Eke tree, in duche ein eich baume, in frenche vng Cheſne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Quinquefolium.</head>
               <p>Quinquefolium is called in greke Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyllon, in engliſh Cynkfoly or fyue fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred graſſe, in duche Funffynger krante, in frenche quinte fuele. Cynkfoly is commune in al places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Radicula.</head>
               <p>Radicula called otherwyſe Lanaria, is called in greeke ſtruthion, and of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune
<pb facs="tcp:5227:46"/> Herbaries it is called Saponaria and Herba fullonum, it groweth in certeine gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dines of Germany, but I neuer ſawe it in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, therfore I know no engliſhe name for it. Howebeit, if we had it here, it myghte be called in engliſh ſopewurt or ſkowrwurt. It is hote and drye in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Radix.</head>
               <p>Radix is called in greeke Raphanos, in engliſhe a radice or radiſhe, in duche ratrich, in frenche raforte. There are two kindes of radice, the one is the commune radice wyth the longe roote, and that is called in latine Radix Cleonea and algide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſis radix. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kynde hath a rounde roote lyke a rape, and thys is called radix Beotia and radix Spriaca. The former kynde groweth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munely in Englande, but I haue ſene the ſeconde kynde no where els ſauynge onely in high Almany, thys maye be called in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe an Alman radice, or rape radice. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice is hote in the thyrde degree and dry in the ſeconde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ranunculus.</head>
               <p>Ranunculus is called in greeke Batra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chion, in engliſhe Crowfote or a Gallande. The kyndes of crowfote are al wel inough knowen ſauyng the ſeconde, whiche if it be vnknowen, it maketh no matter, for it hath
<pb facs="tcp:5227:47"/> more hurte then goodneſſe in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Rapum.</head>
               <p>Rapu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or rapas is called in greeke ſtrog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyle, in engliſhe a rape, in duche ein ruben. Rapes are commune in al countreis.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Rhamnus.</head>
               <p>Rhamnus groweth in the mount Appe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine aboue Bonony, it hath very ſharppe prickes, rounde leaues and fruite lyke a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle buckelet. The inhabiters cal it there ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſts. Wherefore it maye be called in engliſh Chriſtes thorne, or buckeler thorne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Rhus.</head>
               <p>Rhus after Dioſcorides is but of one kynde, but Galene in the boke of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of medicines according to the places nameth two kyndes, the one he calleth Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linaria, and the other Coriaria. Plinie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth three kyndes of Rhois, of the whiche kyndes I knowe one certaynly, whiche is called of the Poticaries Sinnache, and it maye be ſo called alſo in engliſhe. I haue ſene it growyng beſyde Bonony in certeine gardines beſyde the blacke frieres. I thinke that I knowe alſo Rhoa Coriaria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that the ſhrubbe which the Italians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute Bonony cal Scotonum and aboute Cremona cal Rhous, is Rhus Coriaria, for the Italians vſe the ſame to tanne lethre
<pb facs="tcp:5227:47"/> wyth. Thys kynde dyd I fyrſte ſee in Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nony afterwarde beſyde Cremona, laſte in the rockes beſyde Lake de Come. Rhus is drye in the thyrde, and colde in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ricinus.</head>
               <p>Ricinus is called in greeke Cici or Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toon, in engliſh Palma Chriſti, or ticke ſede becauſe it is lyke a tycke, it is called in duch wunden baume, krentz baume and Zekken corner, in french Palma Chriſti. It groweth onely in gardines that I haue ſene.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Roſa.</head>
               <p>Roſa is called in greeke Rhodon, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh a Roſe, in duch ein roſen, in french vne roſe. It is colde and drye in the fyrſt degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Rubia.</head>
               <p>Rubia is called in greeke Erythrodano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in engliſhe madder, in duche rot, in frenche Garauce. Rubia groweth in diuerſe places of Germany in the fieldes in greate plentie both ſet and vnſet. Wilde madder groweth in diuerſe wods of Germany, &amp; in greateſt plentie about Bon. It is hote in the ſeconde degree and dry in the thyrde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Rubus.</head>
               <p>Rubus ſine ſentis is called in greke Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os, in engliſhe a Bramble or a blacke bery buſh, in duche ein bromber, in frenche rouce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:48"/>
               <head>Rubus canis.</head>
               <p>Rubus canis is called in greeke Cynoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batos, in engliſhe a Brier tree or an Hep tree, in duche wylde roſen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Rubus ideus.</head>
               <p>Rubus ideus is called in greeke Batos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>daia, in engliſhe raſpeſes or hyndberies, in duche hyndberen, in frenche framboiſe. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeſes growe moſt plentuouſly in the wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of eaſt Freſelande beſyde Aurik, and in the mountaynes beſyde Bon, they growe alſo in certayne gardines of Englande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Rumex.</head>
               <p>Rumex is called in greeke Lapathon, in engliſh a Docke or a docken. There are .iiij. kyndes of Dockes. The fyrſt kynde is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in greeke Oxylapatho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in engliſhe Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdocke or ſharpdocke. Thys is leſſe then Pacience and wyth a ſharper toppe or ende of the leafe, and groweth in diches &amp; ſlowe runnyng waters, The ſecond kynde is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Rumex ſatiuus, thys is called in barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus latine Reubarbarum monachoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune Docke is of thys ſame kynde. The thirde kynde is the litle commune Docke. The fourth kinde called in greeke Oxalis, in barbarus latin Acetoſa or Acidula, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe Sorel or ſourdocke, in duche ſaur ampſfer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:48"/>
               <head>Ruſcus.</head>
               <p>Ruſcus is called of the Poticeries Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, in engliſh buchers brome or Petigrue. Petigrue groweth in Kent wilde by hedge ſydes, but it beareth no fruite as it doeth in Italy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Ruta.</head>
               <p>Ruta is called in greeke Peganon, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe and frenche, Rue and herbe grace, in duche Ruten. Rue is hote and drye in the ſeconde degree, but wylde Rue is hote and drye in the fourth degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Sabina.</head>
               <p>Sabina is called in greeke Brathy, in engliſhe Sanyne, in duche ſeuinbaume, in frenche ſauinera or du ſauiner. Sauin gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in many gardines in Englande. It is hote and drye in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Sambucus.</head>
               <p>Sambucus or as ſome wryte Sabucus is called in greeke Acte, in engliſhe an El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der tree or a Boure tree, in duche Holde or Hollender, in frenche Vng Suſean.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Salix.</head>
               <p>Salix is called in greeke Itea, in engliſh a wylow tree, a ſalowe tree or a ſaugh tree, in duch weidenbaume, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Vne ſaulge. Salix as Columella wryteth is deuided into two principal kyndes the one is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:5227:49"/> Perticalis, and the other is called Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalis. Particalis ſalix is the greate Wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe tree whyche hath longe roddes and ſtaues growynge in it. Viminalis is an Oſyer tree, ſuche as bryngeth furth rod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that baſkettes are made of. Vimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis is of diuerſe ſortes, the fyrſte is called ſalix greca, the ſeconde gallica, the thirde ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bina. Salix greca whiche is yealowe in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loure groweth in eaſt Freſelande aboute a Citie called Aurik. Salix gallica whiche hath red twigges groweth in many places of Englande. Salix ſabina whiche is alſo called amerina groweth in Italy and in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne places of eaſt Freſelande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Saluia.</head>
               <p>Saluia is called in greeke Eleliſphacos, in engliſhe ſage or ſauge, in duche ſalbey or ſelue, in french ſaulge. It heateth and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge ſtoppeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Satureia.</head>
               <p>Satureia is called in greeke thymbra, in engliſhe ſaueray or ſauery, in duch ſaturei, in frenche ſarriette. It is hote and dry in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Satyrion.</head>
               <p>Satyrion is very commune in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and a certeyne ryghte kynde of the ſame groweth beſyde Syon, it bryngeth furth
<pb facs="tcp:5227:49"/> whyte floures in the ende of harueſte, and it is called Lady traces. The great Satyrion may be called in engliſhe whyte ſatyrion or great ſatyrion. There is an other kynde of Satyrion whiche is called ſatyrion regale in latine, in duche Kreutzblumen, in frenche du ſatyrion royal. Thys maye be called in engliſhe ſatyrion Ryal or hand ſatyrion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is like a mannes hande in the roote. Satyrion is hote and very moyſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Scandix.</head>
               <p>Scandix groweth in Germany among the corne. The greateſt ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of it that euer I ſawe, was betwene Bon and Popelſdorp in a corne fielde. It may be called in engliſh corne Cheruel. It is hote &amp; dry in the thirde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Secale.</head>
               <p>Secale is called in engliſhe Rye, in duche Roggen or rug, in frenche Segle, There is plentie inough of rye in al countreis, and no where more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Germany, that I wotof</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Scilla.</head>
               <p>Scilla is named of the Poticaries ſquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, in engliſh a ſea Onion, and in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, a french Onyon, in duch Meuſz Zwy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beln. Squilles growe in the ſea coſte of Spayne in greate plentie. Scilla is hote in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:50"/>
               <head>Scirpus.</head>
               <p>Scirpus ſiue Iuncus is called in greeke Scoinos Eleos, in engliſh a riſhe or a raſhe, in duche Bauchbint, in frenche Ioue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Scordium.</head>
               <p>Scordium groweth in diuerſe places of Germany, &amp; is ſolde at Franckeforde mart in greate plentie, &amp; I heare ſaye that it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth alſo beſyde Oxforde. It is called in duche Waſſer batenig, and it maye be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in engliſhe water Germander or Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leke Germander.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Scordotis.</head>
               <p>Scordotis altera wherof Plinie maketh mention, is in leaues muche lyke a Nettle, but deaper endented wyth a foure ſquared ſtalke, and wyth a ſomthynge ſharpe taſte, it groweth aboute the Rhene ſyde. Some take thys for Verbena recta, but it hath no purple floures, wherfore they are deceyued. It maye be called in engliſhe banke Nettle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Securidaca.</head>
               <p>Securidaca called in greeke Edyſaron and Pelecinos, is ſo vnknowen in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and in Germany that I neuer ſawe it in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe regions, but I haue ſene it in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly dyuerſe tymes, and it maye be called in engliſhe Axfiche or Hachetfiche, becauſe the ſeede reſembleth an Hatchet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:50"/>
               <head>Sedum.</head>
               <p>Sedum is called in greke Aeizooon, and the fyrſte kynde and moſte ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of, of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, is called in engliſhe Houſleke or ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene. The ſeconde kynde is called in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh thryft or ſtoneroppe The thyrd kinde is called in Engliſhe Mouſe tayle or litle ſtoneroppe, and in duche Maur pfeſſer. Al theſe kyndes growe on walles and houſes. It is colde in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Senecio.</head>
               <p>Senecio is called in greke Erigeroon, in engliſh Groundſwel or Groundſel, in duch Gryntkraut, in frenche du Seneſſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Serpyllum.</head>
               <p>Serpyllum called in greeke Irpyllon, is of .ij. ſortes. The one is called in latine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyllum Hortenſe, and in engliſhe runnyng tyme. The ſeconde kynde is called in latine ſerpyllum ſylueſtre, and in engliſhe wylde tyme. The one groweth in gardines, &amp; the other in ſandy fieldes and bare groundes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Sertula campana.</head>
               <p>Sertula ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pana ſiue corona regia, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in greeke Melilootos, in duch Gulden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, in Welſher, ſteyncle, in french du Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilote. I neuer ſawe the ryghte Melilote yet in England, but I haue ſene the right Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilute which groweth in Italy, &amp; hath ſeedes
<pb facs="tcp:5227:51"/> in litle hornes. This herbe whiche ye vſe in Englande for Melilote, is a kynde of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſylueſtris. This ryght Melilotus may be called in engliſhe Melilote, or right Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilote, or Lumberdy Melilote. Melilote is hote and dry en the fyrſt degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Seſama.</head>
               <p>Seſama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n dyd I neuer ſee in England, but I haue ſene it in Italy, and it maye be called in engliſhe, ſeſame or oyle ſeede, for of al ſeede it is moſte oylie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Seſeli maſſilienſe.</head>
               <p>Seſeli maſſilienſe is called in the Potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhoppes, ſiler montanum, it may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in engliſhe, ſiler mountayne. The ſeede of thys herbe is commune in euery Potica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhoppe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Siligo.</head>
               <p>Siligo is not as the commune ſorte of grammarians and phiſicians ſuppoſe, the corne called in engliſhe Rye, and in duche Rog, but it is a kynde of ryghte wheate, as Columella and Plinie do teſtifie. Therfore let it be called in engliſhe lyght wheate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Sideritis.</head>
               <p>Sideritis prima, groweth vpon Colon walies and alſo in ſandy groundes aboute Colon. It is called in duch Glyderant, and may be called in engliſhe walſage or ſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.
<pb facs="tcp:5227:51"/> Sideritis ſecunda, is moſt lyke to Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tide of the Poticaries, of al herbes that euer I ſawe, and nothyng is contrary vnto the deſcription ſauynge onely the ſeedes. Sideritis tertia ſemeth to be the herbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in engliſhe, herbe Roberte wyth the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues lyke Colander.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Siliqua.</head>
               <p>Siliqua is not as the commune ſort take it for the ſhale onely of a peaſcod, or of ſuch lyke pulſe, but it is taken for a certeine tree, and fruite which is called in greke Ceratia, or Ceratonia, in Italian Carobe, in duche ſaynte Iohans Brot. I met wyth certeyne Grecians whiche dwelled in Pelopeneſo, that called it in their ſpeache Xylocerato<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Itmay be called in engliſh a Carobe tree, and the fruite Carobes or Carobbeanes. I ſe in Colon one litle Carob tree, and no where els that I remembre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Sinapi.</head>
               <p>Sinapi is called in greeke ſinepi, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe Muſtarde, in duche ſenſe, in frenche Muſtarde. It groweth in al countreis in plentie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Siſaron.</head>
               <p>Siſaron ſiue ſiſer, is called in engliſhe a Perſnepe, in duche groſſe Zammoren, and alſo Pinſternach, Fuchſius rekeneth that
<pb facs="tcp:5227:52"/> our ſhyrwort, or ſhyrwit is a kynde of ſiſer. Perſuepes, and ſkirwortes are commune in Englande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Siſon.</head>
               <p>Siſon called of other Sino<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is the herbe whoſe ſeede the Poticaries in Anwerp vſe for Amomo. Ther groweth a kinde of this beſyde Shene, and it maye be called in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe wylde Perſeley. The beſt kinde gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in Anthony the Poticaries gardine of Anwerp.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Siſymbrium.</head>
               <p>Siſymbrium horte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe is called in engliſhe haume Mynte, or water Mynte, in duche fiſhe Mynt, or waſſer Muntz. Many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne the red Mynt that groweth by water ſydes, and is called of ſome horſe Mynt vnder ſiſymbrio. It is hote and drye in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Siſymbrium alterum.</head>
               <p>Siſymbrium alterum is called alſo Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damine, and in engliſh water creſſes, or roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket water creſſes, in duche waſſerkreſſich, in frenche du Creſſon. Thys is not the herbe with leaues lyke Perſeley communely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led water Creſſes, but it is the true water Creſſe wyth leaues lyke Rocket, and ſome cal it in latin Naſturtium aquaticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth muche in brokes and water ſydes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:52"/>
               <head>Smilax hortenſis.</head>
               <p>Smilax horte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſis is called in duch welſhe arbs or welſhe Bonen, in frenche as ſome wryte Phaſcole. It may be called in engliſh Kydney beane, becauſe the ſeede is lyke a Kydney, or arber beanes, becauſe they ſerue to couer an arber for the tyme of Summer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Sinilax aſpera.</head>
               <p>Smilax aſpera groweth not in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that euer I coulde ſee, I haue ſene it in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many where it is called groſſe Stechend wynde, or ſhraffe wynde. It maye be called in engliſhe Pryckewynde or Sharpbynde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Smyrnium.</head>
               <p>Smyrniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is neither Angelica nor yet Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage. I dyd ſee it once in Bonony. It maye be called in engliſhe blacke Louage, becauſe it hath leaues lyke Louage, and yet blacke ſeede. It is hote &amp; dry in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Solanum hortenſe.</head>
               <p>Solanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> horte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe which is called in greke Strichnos Cepaios is called in Engliſhe Nyghtſhade, or pety morel, in duche Nach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhat, in frenche Morel. The Poticaries cal it Solatrum.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Solanum veſicarium.</head>
               <p>Solanum veſicarium is called in greeke Strichnos halicacabos, in Pottcarie latin Alkakenge, in engliſhe Alcakeng or wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:5227:53"/> cheries, in duche Iudenkyrſe, in frenche Baganauldes. Thys herbe groweth much in my Lordes gardine at Syon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Sorbus.</head>
               <p>There are foure kyndes of ſorbus after Plinie, of the which I knowe three kyndes. The fyrſt kynde that I knowe is commune aboute Bon. It hath leaues lyke a quicken tree, and a fruite lyke a litle Peare, the duch cal it ein ſpeirlyng, and ein ſporopfel. This tree maye be called in engliſhe a ſorb tree, and the fruite a ſorb Appel. The ſeconde kynde is called in duche ein Hauer aſhe, in engliſhe a rountree or a Quicken tree. The third kinde that I knowe of ſorbus and the fourth kynde in Plinie is called ſorbus tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalis, in engliſhe a ſeruice tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Spartum frutex.</head>
               <p>Spartium or ſpartum is not the Broume that we make beſomes of in Englande, but it is a buſhe called of ſome gardiners frenche brome. It groweth naturally by it ſelfe in mount Appenuine, and it is founde nowe in many gardines in England, in my Lordes gardine at Shene, and in my Lorde Cobbains gardin a litle fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Graues Ende</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Spartum herba.</head>
               <p>Spartum is alſo an herbe as Plinie wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, by whoſe deſcription I gather that it
<pb facs="tcp:5227:53"/> is the riſhe that the Fig frayles be made of, I haue ſene that riſhe in the Ilandes of eaſt Freſeland, and the people there make ropes of that riſhe &amp; thach their houſes alſo wyth the ſame It may be called in engliſh Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Sphondilium.</head>
               <p>Sphondilium is called in duche wylde Pateney, or wylde Bereuklawe, in frenche Panaie ſauage. It may be called in engliſhe Cowpertſnepe or rough Perſnepe. It gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in watery middowes and in raine groundes about hedges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Spina alba.</head>
               <p>Spina alba mentioned in Columella is ſpina Appendix in Plinie, and it is called in engliſhe an Hawthorne tree, or a whyte thorne, in duche ein wiſſen dorne, or ein Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendorne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Stachys.</head>
               <p>Stachys ſemeth to Geſner to be the herbe that we cal in engliſh Ambroſe, &amp; I deni not but that it may be a kynde of it, Howe be it I haue ſene the true Italian ſtaches, whiche hath narower and whyter leaues then Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe hath. It maye benamed in engliſhe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Horehounde or ſtrayte Horehound. It is hote in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Staphis agria.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:54"/>
               <p>Staphis agria is called in engliſhe ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues aker, in duch Biſz muntz or Lanſhraut, in frenche de lee ſtaues agrie. I haue ſene it growyng in certeyne gardines in Italy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Sterhas.</head>
               <p>I haue ſene in Italy diuerſe kyndes of Stichados growyng. One was called ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhas mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tana, an other ſtechas prouincialis, and the thyrd ſtechas Arabia. I neuer ſawe any of theſe kyndes growyng in England, but I haue had them growynge in my gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines in Germany. The herbe may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in engliſh ſtichas, or Laua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der gentle, the Poticaries cal thys herbe ſtichados. I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that our laua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der is a kinde of ſtichas. It is hote in the firſt degree &amp; dry in the ſecond.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Symphytum.</head>
               <p>Symphytum is of two ſortes, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is called Symphytum petreum, and this herbe groweth about Syon, ſeuen my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les aboue London. It is lyke vnto wylde Mergerum, but it is neither ſo hote neither ſo wel ſmellyng. It may be called in engliſh vnſauery Mergerſi. The other kynde cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in latin Symphytum alterum, is called in engliſhe comfrey or Blackewurt, and in duche walde wurtz, or ſchwartz wurtz, in frenche de la confire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Tarchon.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:54"/>
               <p>Tarchon is wel knowen in Englande, and is called wyth vs Tarrago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Some cal thys ſame herbe Dracoue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> horte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſem Some other do put thys herbe vnto the kyndes of Sauery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Taxus.</head>
               <p>Taxus is called in greke Smilar or tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os, in engliſhe an Vghe tree, or an yew tree, in duch ein Iben baume, in french <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ff The beſte Vghe groweth in the Alpes. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune Vghe, groweth in diuerſe partes of Yorke ſhyre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Thapſia.</head>
               <p>Thapſia groweth in diuerſe places of Italy that I haue ſene, and the beſte learned of that countrey thynke that Meſues tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit is Thapſia. Thapſia maye be called in engliſhe thapfene, or thapſia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Thlaſpi.</head>
               <p>Thlaſpi or thlaſpium is called in duche Baurenfenſe It groweth wonders plentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly about Bon in the corne fieldes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the corne. It groweth alſo ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuouſly beſyde Syon. It may be named in engliſhe dyſmuſtard, or triacle Muſtard, or Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es Muſtard, becauſe the ſeede is lyke mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard ſeede in colour and in taſt, and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſel that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyneth the ſeed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is lyke a diſſhe. There is yet an other kinde of thlaſpie me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb facs="tcp:5227:55"/> of Dioſcorides and called thlaſpi al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum &amp; ſinapi perſicuum. This kinde gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in Morpeth in Northumberland and there it is called Redco. It ſhoulde be called after the olde ſaxon engliſhe Rettihcol, that is Radiſhe colle. The high Germans cal it mere Rettich.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Thymus.</head>
               <p>We gather boeth by Dioſcorides &amp; Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, that there are two kyndes of Thyme, whereof I ſee but one kinde as yet in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, for that runnyng thyme that we take for thymo, is ſerpyllum and not thymus.</p>
               <p>The greate kynde of thyme, wherof Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcorides maketh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of in Epithymo, is called nowe Venetian thyme, and the blacke kynde that Plinie ſpeaketh of, is oure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune thyme that groweth ryght vp in our gardines. Thyme is hote in the thyrde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Tuſſilago.</head>
               <p>Tuſſilago is called in greeke Bechion, in engliſhe Bulfote or horſehofe, in duche Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhub, or houfe lattich, in fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch Pas de Aſne, the Poticaries cal it Vngulam caballinam. Thys herbe groweth by water ſydes, and in mariſhe groundes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Typha.</head>
               <p>Typha groweth in fennes &amp; waterſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:5227:55"/> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the reedes, it hath a blacke thinge Almoſt at the head of the ſtalke lyke blacke Veluet. It is called in engliſhe cattes tayle, or a Reedmace, in Duche Narren Kolb, or Moſz Kolb.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Verbaſcum.</head>
               <p>Verbaſcum is called in greke Phlomos, in engliſhe Mullen higgis taper or Longe wurt, the Poticaries cal it tapſus barbatus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Verbaſculum.</head>
               <p>There are .iij. Verbaſcula called in greke Phlomides. The fyrſte is called in barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus latin Arthritica, and in engliſhe a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meroſe. The ſeconde is called in barbarus latin Paralyſis, and in engliſhe a Cowſlip, or a Cowſlap, or a Pagle. The third is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Thryallis, and Roſecampi in engliſhe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Verbenaca.</head>
               <p>Verbenaca recta is called in greeke Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtereon yphos, in engliſh Veruine, in duch Eiſer kraute, in frenche Veruayne. Thys herbe groweth in many places of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Verbena ſupina, is harde to fynde in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande I neuer ſawe it in any place ſauynge in Swycherland. It is lyke Bugle, but the leaues are deaplyer endented &amp; grener then bugle leaues be. It may be called in engliſh geagged Bugle. It groweth in ſhadowye places about tree rootes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:56"/>
               <head>Veratrum.</head>
               <p>Veratrum is called in greke Helleborus in duche Nieſz wurtes, in frenche Viraire. It maye be called in engliſhe Neſewurte. There are two kyndes of Helleborus, the one is called Veratrum album, and it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in duche Wiſz Neiſzwurtes, in engliſhe Neſewurt or whyte Neſewurt. This kinde groweth in Syon Parcke in Englande, in the woddes of Bon in Germany, in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes betwene Curela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and Lumberdy, but it that groweth in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hath not the ſtrength that it hath whiche groweth in the Alpes. The other kynde is called Veratrum nigrum. I haue not ſene thys herbe in Germany, neither in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande. For the herbe called in engliſhe bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fote, in duche Chriſtwurte, which hath bene hyther to taken for blacke Niſewurt, or Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratrum nigrum: is Conſiligo in Columel and Plinie, and not veratrum nigrum.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Vicia.</head>
               <p>Vicia is called in greeke Bicion, in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe a Fiche, in duche Wicken, in frenche La veſce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Viola alba.</head>
               <p>Viola alba is called in greeke Leucoion. There are diuerſe ſortes of Leuecoio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. One is called in engliſh Cheiry, Hertes eaſe or wal
<pb facs="tcp:5227:56"/> Gelefloure, it groweth vpon the walles, and in the ſprynge of the yere, it hath yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe floures. The Arabians cal it Cheiri. An other kynde hath whyte floures, whiche ſome cal whyte ſtocke gelefloure or Bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noures. The other haue purple and blewe floures, and are called purple &amp; blew ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gele floures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Viola nigra.</head>
               <p>Viola nigra ſiue purpurea is called in greeke Ion melan, in engliſhe a Violet, in duche violen, Viole or Violette, in frenche Violet martie. It is colde and moyſte in the ſeconde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Viola flammea.</head>
               <p>Viola flommea otherwyſe called Phlox or Phlogion is the herbe as Geſner thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, whiche is called in duche Fluelblum, and in engliſhe veluet floure or french Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigoulde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Viſcum.</head>
               <p>Viſcum is called in greeke Ixos, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleſh Miſcelto or Miſceldin, in duch Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, Vogellym, and Affoler in french. This ſhrub groweth only in trees &amp; no where els</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Vitex</head>
               <p>Vitex is called in greeke Agnos, of the Poticaries of Italy Agnus caſtus, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaries of Germany in netherlande abuſe Lign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5227:57"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaries in Germany abuſe thys herbe for Scordio. Thys herbe groweth in hedges and diches in the ſprynge of the yere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Balſamine.</head>
               <p>Balſamine is called of other Pomu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſolymitanum, &amp; Pomum mirabile. Some cal it Chara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia. It is called in duch Balſam kraute, it maye be named in engliſhe Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam aple. It groweth muche in Italy and in ſome places of Germany, but onely in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Barbare herba.</head>
               <p>Barbare herba groweth aboute Brokes and water ſydes. It hath leaues lyke Roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, wherefore it maye be called in engliſhe woundrocket, for it is good for a wounde. Some cal thys Carpentariam.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Bipennella Italica.</head>
               <p>Bipennella or bipenula Italica, is called in engliſh Burnet. It groweth much about Syon and Shene, and in many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. The Poticaries cal it Pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinellam.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Bipennula Germanica.</head>
               <p>Bipennula Germanica, is Saxifragia Italorum, and it is called in engliſhe Pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piuel, the duche cal it Bibinellen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Biſtorta.</head>
               <p>Biſtorta is called of the Northerne men
<pb facs="tcp:5227:57"/> Betes, in the South countrey Aſtrologia, in eaſt Freſelande Leuercraut. Thys herbe groweth in Englande onely in gardines, in the woddes of Freſeland, it groweth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſettyng alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Burſa paſtoris.</head>
               <p>Burſa paſtoris is alſo called in engliſhe of many Burſa paſtoris &amp; of other Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdes bag or Shepherdes purſe. It gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth by high wayes, almoſt in euery place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cartafilago.</head>
               <p>Cartafilago otherwiſe called Ceratophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lax, is called in engliſh Cudwurt or Chafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wurte, It groweth gladly where as turnes haue ben digged.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Conſolida media.</head>
               <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolida media is called in engliſh Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle. It is a blacke herbe and it groweth in ſhaddowy places and moyſt groundes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Cornu ceruinum.</head>
               <p>Cornu ceruinum is the name of three her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes. The fyrſt is Coronopus, the ſeconde is Hartes horne lyke a riſhe, the thyrd is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the dioces of Colo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath leaues lyke an Hartes horne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Chriſtophoriana.</head>
               <p>Chriſtophoriana groweth ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuouſly in the woddes aboute Bon, but I haue not hearde any duche name that it hath. It may be
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5227:58"/> the duch cal it Natter Zunglin. It groweth ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuouſly in middowes where as Lunary groweth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Leuiſticum.</head>
               <p>Leuiſticum is called in engliſhe Louage in duche Lubſtocke or Lieb ſtokel, in french Liueſhe. It groweth onely in gardines ſo muche as I haue ſene.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Martagon.</head>
               <p>Martagon is an herbe wyth two leaues onely, one of ech ſyde. It groweth in many places of Englande in watery middowes and in woddes. It is alſo called in engliſhe Martagon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Perfoliata.</head>
               <p>Perfoliata is an herbe wyth a leafe lyke a peaſe, &amp; litle blacke ſeedes in the top. The Germans cal it Durchwaſſz. It maye be called in engliſhe Thorowwax, becauſe the ſtalke waxeth thorowe the leaues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Pes anſerinus.</head>
               <p>Pes anſerinus is called in duch geuſz fuſz, and it may be called in engliſhe Gooſef ote. It groweth in the fieldes of Germany a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the corne and aboute townes &amp; cities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Piloſella.</head>
               <p>Piloſella is of two kyndes, the one hath a yealowe floure and is communely called in engliſh Mouſeare, and for difference ſake
<pb facs="tcp:5227:58"/> it may be called in engliſh yealowe mouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eare. The other kynde hath purple floures mengled wyth whyte altogether, and thys groweth in heathes where as King or heath groweth, and may be called in engliſh pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Mouſeare or litle Mouſeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Portentilla.</head>
               <p>Porte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilla or as ſome write Potentilla, is named alſo Tanacetum ſylueſtre. It is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in englyſhe wylde Canſey, in duche Genſeric h, &amp; in french Taunaſi Saluage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Regalicum.</head>
               <p>Regalicum is alſo named Ruta cararia, Galega, &amp; Gaiarda. It groweth very plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly about the bankes of Padus in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. It maye be called in engliſhe mocke Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cores, becauſe the leaues are lyke Licores.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Rhibes.</head>
               <p>Rhibes is called in duche ſaynte Iohans Treublin, and it is called in ſome places of Englande a Raſin tree.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Sanicula.</head>
               <p>Sanicula is named in engliſhe Sanicle, in duche Sanikel or Sharnikel. It groweth communely in woddes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Saluia vita.</head>
               <p>Saluia vita or Ruta muralis is called in duche Maurtanten &amp; ſteinrauten. It maye be called in engliſh Stone Rue or wal Rue
<pb facs="tcp:5227:59"/> Some haue vſed this for Capillo Veneris.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Solidago ſaracenica.</head>
               <p>Solidago ſeracenica, otherwyſe called Herba fortis or Herba Iudaica, is called in duch Heidniſhe wuntkrant. I haue not ſene it in Englande, but diuerſe tymes in duch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. It may be called in engliſh Wounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wurte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Scabioſa.</head>
               <p>Scabioſa is called in engliſhe Scabious or Maifellon, in duche Scabioſen, in french la ſcabieuſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Saxifragia.</head>
               <p>There are foure herbes, whiche al are called ſaxifragia. The engliſhe mens Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ifragia, which they cal Saxifrage, hath lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues lyke ſmal perſeley, &amp; it groweth in mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes. The Italians ſaxifragia is lyke the ſame, but it hath rougher leaues and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; an hotter roote. The Germayns haue two Saxifrages, whiche other countreis know not by thoſe names. The greater hath greate leaues, lyke ſmallage, and yealowe iuice in the ſtalke, and this is called of other wryters Viride Marcum. It may be call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in engliſhe, grene Marke. Thys groweth muche by the Temmes ſyde about Sheue. The other duche ſaxifrage hath leaues lyke Tyme, &amp; it may be called in engliſh Time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonebreake.
<pb facs="tcp:5227:59"/> I haue not ſene it in England. It groweth in ſandy groundes aboute the Rhene.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Tormentilla.</head>
               <p>Tormentilla is called in greeke Hepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyllon, in engliſhe Tormentil, or Torme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rik, in duche Torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>til. It groweth in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and Heathes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Trinitaria or trinitatis herba.</head>
               <p>Trinitatis herba, is of two ſortes. The one hath leaues lyke a Clarier, and it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in the Alpes, and other highe moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes. It may be called in engliſh mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifoly The other kinde is called in engliſh two faces in a hoode or pauſes. Thys is like vnto a Violet in the floures, and it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth ofte amonge the corne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Vua criſpa.</head>
               <p>Vua criſpa is alſo called Groſſularia, in engliſh a Groſer buſhe, a Gooſebery buſh. It groweth onely that I haue ſene in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, in gardines, but I haue ſene it in Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>many a brode in the fieldes amonge other buſſhes</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Veronica.</head>
               <p>Veronica groweth in many places of England, and it is called in engliſhe Fluel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, in duche Erenpriſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Vuluaria.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Vuluaria is a ſtynkyng herbe creapynge by the grounde with leaues of Mergerum or Organe. It groweth muche aboute the walles of Bon in Germany. I did ſe it alſo in my Lorde Cobbains gardine at Calice.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_English_plant_names">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A table for the commune engliſh names vſed nowe in al countreis of Englande.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Loe Agarik, Auenes, Arſſmert Aſtrologia, Adders tong, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple tree, Abrecok, Alexander, Alkakenge</p>
            <p>Baye tree, Barley, Baſyll, Burnette, Broume pricki, Broume, Belragges, Brier brake, Bramble, Bulfote, Butter bur, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers broume, Bulfot, Bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke vrſme Baume Baume, Mynte, Birche, Bene, Brokelem, Beech tree, Blewblawe, Bynde corne.</p>
            <p>Camamil, Chickeweede, Citterach, Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, Capers, Cuckowe pintle, Caraweis, Caret wylde, Corne Mynte, Comyn, Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Cheruel, Celendine, Crowe toes. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, Creſſe of the gardine, Creſſe of the water, Cheſnut, Clarie, Cuckowes meate, Comfrey.</p>
            <p>Duckes meate, Dittany, Dittany of Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, Darnel, Dragon, Date tree, Dogges
<pb facs="tcp:5227:60"/> tonge, Docke, Daffadyl, Daffadyl duche, Daſy, Doder.</p>
            <p>Ehu tree, Earthnut, Egle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine, Endyue Elecampane.</p>
            <p>Foxgloue, Fluellin, Filipendula, Fiche, Firtree, Flouramor, Fumitory, Figtree, Ferne, Fenel, Fenegreke.</p>
            <p>Gala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ga, Garleke, Garleke wyld, wilde Gooſegraſſe, Goteſbearde, Gourd, Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane, Gooſeberies, Graſſe, Gethſamyne, Grummell, Groundſel.</p>
            <p>Hartes horne, Hyſope, Hoppes, Hore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounde, Homſuccles, Hartes tonge, Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leke He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bayne, Horehounde ſtinkyng, Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, Herbe Iue, Haſel, Heath, Hulner or Holy of the ſea.</p>
            <p>Iacke of the hedge, Iuniper.</p>
            <p>Knotgraſſe.</p>
            <p>Ladies mantel, Lunary, Louage, Licores, Lettes, Laurel, Lauriel, Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilles, Liuerwurt, Louage of Lumberdy, Litle licke, Lange de beefe, Ladies traces.</p>
            <p>Mallowe, Mallowe verueyn, Moſſe, Mynt, corne Marygolde, Mayden heire, Martagon, Mouſeare, Maſtike tree, Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dragge, Mynt, Mercury, Medler, Mewe, Mulbery, Melilote, Muſtarde, Mullem, Muſcelto.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5227:61"/>
            <p>Nigella romana, Nettel, Nighteſhade, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe. ¶ Orege, Orenge, Otes, Oke, Oke of Hieruſalem, Onyon, Organ.</p>
            <p>Prymet, Pomgarnat, Piony, Popy, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre, Pyneaple, Peaſe, Plantaine, Popler, Purcellaine, Plame tree, Penirial, Peartree, Palina Chriſti, Pech tree, Perſuepe.</p>
            <p>Quicken tree.</p>
            <p>Raſin tree, Roſemary, Ryſe, Radice, Rape, Roſe, Raſpiſes, Rue, Rye, Ryſhes, Ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pious, Ramſes, Rampes, Reede, Rocket,</p>
            <p>Sowthiſtle, Saynte Iohans graſſe. Spourge, Sperage, Slauke, Saffro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, Saffron wylde, Sene, Sampere, Stoncrop, Strawbery, Syues, Shepher, des bag, Sanicle, Saxifrage, Staues aker Succory ſetwal, Scala celi, Sauine, Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe. Sage, Sauery, Satyrion.</p>
            <p>Twopeny graſſe, Thorowwax, Tor mentil, Two faces in a hode, Tamariſke Turnepe, Tyme, wylde Tyme, Thorne tree, Tarragon, Thiſtle cotton, Trifoly, Turſan, Taſel wylde.</p>
            <p>Wormwodde, Wulfes bayne Venus, heire, Veluet floure purple, water lyly, Wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter betony, Wodbyne, Vinde, Wad, Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wurt, Weybent, Walnut, Vinewild, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter roſe waybrade, Whyte roote, Wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, Vghe, Verueyne, Violet.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:5227:61"/>
            <head>Fautes eſcaped in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng.</head>
            <list>
               <item>In Ariſtolochia: read Oſterluci, for Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Luci.</item>
               <item>In Aſclepias, reade wurt, for wixt.</item>
               <item>In Beta, reade Plinie, for Plenie.</item>
               <item>In Caſtenea, read Dioſbalanos, for Dos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balanos.</item>
               <item>In Cicerbita, read Haſcukoel, for Saſenkoel</item>
               <item>In Circium, read flour for herbe.</item>
               <item>In Ciſthus ladanifera, read Laudan, for London.</item>
               <item>In Clinopodium, read Rhene, for Rehne</item>
               <item>In Dictamnus, reade Trarinella, for Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinella.</item>
               <item>In Ebulus, reade for Allich, Attich.</item>
               <item>In Eriſe, for Frith, Hethes.</item>
               <item>In Goſcipium, for Pylon, Xylon</item>
               <item>In Hordium murinum, for Plenie, Plinie</item>
               <item>In Irio, for Cerſſe, Kerſſe.</item>
               <item>In Libanotis, reade ſecond degree.</item>
               <item>In Limonium, read for wintergrowen: win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergrune.</item>
               <item>In Lolmin, read Aera, for Ara</item>
               <item>In Marubium, read witen for welen.</item>
               <item>In Narciſſus, reade Plinie, for Plenie</item>
               <item>In Papauer, read Manſom, for Manſom.</item>
               <item>In Ranunculus, read Golland for Galland</item>
               <item>In Rapum, reade Rapa, for Rapas</item>
               <item>In Serpyllum, reade Erpyllon, for Iepyllo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:5227:62"/>
               <item>In Sideritis, reade Gliderant, for Glide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raut.</item>
               <item>In Sphondilium, reade Paſteney, for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teney.</item>
               <item>In Stechas, read arabica, for Arabia.</item>
               <item>In Thalſpi, for Baurenfenfe: reade Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renſenfe.</item>
               <item>In vitis Sylueſtris, for Heguine, read Hedg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uine.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Imprinted</hi> at London by Iohn Day and Wyllyam Seres, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge in Sepulchres Pariſh at the ſigne of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection a litle aboue Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourne Conduite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Cum gratia &amp; priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5227:62"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
